<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The conformists plea for the nonconformists, or, A just and compassionate representation of the present state and condition of the non-conformists as to I. The greatness of their sufferings, II. Hardness of their case, III. Reasonableness and equity of their desires and proposals, IV. Qualifications, and worth of their persons, V. Peaceableness of their behaviour, VI. The churches prejudice by their exclusion, &amp;c. humbly submitted to authority / by a beneficed minister, and a regular son of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Pearse, Edward, 1631-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56807</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P976</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1092</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11875652</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11875652</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50217</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56807)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50217)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 504:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The conformists plea for the nonconformists, or, A just and compassionate representation of the present state and condition of the non-conformists as to I. The greatness of their sufferings, II. Hardness of their case, III. Reasonableness and equity of their desires and proposals, IV. Qualifications, and worth of their persons, V. Peaceableness of their behaviour, VI. The churches prejudice by their exclusion, &amp;c. humbly submitted to authority / by a beneficed minister, and a regular son of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Pearse, Edward, 1631-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 67 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Pearse.  Cf.  Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Errata on prelim. p. [7].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50217:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Conformiſts Plea FOR THE Nonconformiſts.</p>
            <p>OR, A Juſt and Compaſſionate Repreſentation OF THE Preſent State and Condition OF THE NON-CONFORMISTS.</p>
            <list>
               <label>AS TO</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. The Greatneſs of their Sufferings.</item>
                     <item>II. Hardneſs of their Caſe.</item>
                     <item>III. Reaſonableneſs and Equity of their Deſires and Propoſals.</item>
                     <item>IV. Qualifications, and Worth of their Perſons.</item>
                     <item>V. Peaceableneſs of their Behaviour.</item>
                     <item>VI. The Churches Prejudice by their Excluſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Humbly ſubmitted to Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Beneficed Miniſter, and a Regular Son of the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon,</hi> at the Golden Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:50217:2"/>
            <head>His Majeſty's Speech to both Houſes of Parliament, <hi>Monday,</hi> Feb. 10. 1667. <hi>pag.</hi> 4.</head>
            <p>—One thing more I hold my Self obliged to recommend unto you at this preſent; which is, That you would ſeriouſly think of ſome Courſe to beget a better Vnion and Compoſure in the Minds of my Proteſtant Subjects, in Matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, whereby they may be induced, not only to ſubmit quietly to the Government, but alſo chearfully give their Aſſiſtance to the ſupport of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_bookseller">
            <pb facs="tcp:50217:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50217:3"/>
            <head>To the Bookſeller.</head>
            <p>COnceiving it to be a Duty to communicate my Judgment (given privately by Parts, as occaſion hath been offered) of the <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> and their Caſe, and alſo reſolved to conceal my Name, which can add no Reputation to them, nor to theſe Papers; I have ſent them to you, before any other Stranger, (and who but a Stranger may be truſted with a Concealment of one he knows not) for two Reaſons. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, one of your Acquaintance, who (not knowing my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign) gave me a very good Character of you, as Ingenuous, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, Candid, a lover of Goodneſs and good Men, (whether <hi>Conformiſts</hi> or <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi>) as well without, as within the way of your Trade. 2. Becauſe it is not hard to gueſs at the Bookſeller by his Author, and the Author by his Bookſeller; therefore if you may fall within the compaſs of this Obſervation, you fit me, becauſe you printed the <hi>Conforming Non-conformiſt,</hi> &amp;c. And another, the <hi>Chriſtian Temper,</hi> which Title was taking with me, (a Temper rare among Chriſtians) which I labour after; and if I have not expreſſed it in theſe Sheets, I ſhall take as little pleaſure in them, as the niceſt Reader ſhall in any thing that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from him. I refer it to you to judg, whether it is like to be profitable or not: for before the publication of Books, your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty either are Judges, or find out Judges of them; and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders eat, or refuſe, only what you have taſted of before-hand. Read and judg deliberately, and let me know e're long of your Approbation, by ſeeing it abroad; or your diſlike, by its ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And then I have but one Requeſt, that you would give them a private and a decent Burial, for the Author's ſake; who tho he be but a ſimple Man, yet means well, and for his Maſter's ſake: It ſhall no more offend me that you ſtifle, than that if ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take the name of them, provided he be <hi>Philagathos.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:50217:4"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>THe whole Book is to the Reader, yet a ſhort Epiſtle to him may be neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> To intreat him to ſpare his pains in writing againſt me, who do not begin or maintain a Controverſy againſt him, or againſt any other; <hi>Pacem te quaerimus omnes.</hi> You may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſeek to keep it within the unaltered Conſtitution, and be ſo much for Peace, that you would have not one Diſſenter in the Land. I am against Diſſenters alſo, we agree ſo far; but I am against Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters within doors, that keep Diſſenters out; let us make up the Breach as fast and as ſtrong as we can.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> To inform him, that I do not look upon the Nonconformiſts as the only Men of God, that I am not hired by them nor ſpeak for them in hopes of Preferment under the Presbyterian Government, to be ſet up (as ſome fear) I aſſure him I never fear it, nor hope for it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> To make my ſelf known to him, that I am not a Man in Power to ſhew the Non-conformiſts favour, nor a Man of fame to ſerve them by any Teſtimonial; but that I laboured to nouriſh ſome good Diſpoſitions and Qualities.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> To adore one and the ſame Spirit in different Gifts, Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, and Degrees.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> To think more highly of others than of my ſelf, not only as they are in Power, but as in real Worth, tho but at the Footſtool.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Thankfulneſs to God; and were it in my power to ſhew it to every one that ever ſpake a word in ſeaſon to me, which many of the Non-conformists have done, when I was ignorant and out of the way, whoſe Names are in honour with me; and the like I acknowledg, and ever ſhall, to ſeveral that now conform. Time was, when they all ſpake the ſame Things, and carried on the ſame Work; which was the Inſtruction, Converſion, Conſolation, and Edification of Souls; not biting one another, nor grudging at one another. I never heard,
<pb facs="tcp:50217:4"/>in many hundreds of Sermons, diverſities of Opinions, either ſet up by ſome, or pulled down by others. We heard indeed that ſome were Independents, others Presbyterians, and others Epiſcopal, but we heard no ſuch things from Pulpits. I perceive ſome Men think that the preaching of thoſe Days was meer Fanaticiſm, bleſſing the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation, railing against Biſhops, or deifying <hi>Calvin</hi> with an Infallibility; <hi>Non ego</hi> Lutherum <hi>praedico, ſed Chriſtum,</hi> ſaid <hi>Luther. Calvin</hi> was an admirable Man, a great Stranger to them that ſpeak moſt againſt him; but he was preached no further than Christ ſpake in him; <hi>Non Calvinum ſed Chriſtum praedicabant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> If I were partial, I wrong my ſelf by partiality, but I ought to be juſt, and by being just, I injure no Man. I have heard the Non-conformiſts vilified, and repreſented according to the Fancies, and Paſſions, or Interests of Men. I durst not but be just to them, as to eminent Profeſſors of the Christian Faith, and think that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Christianity hath ſuffered much by their ſilencing and diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. A great part of the World is made to believe, that the Non-conformiſts are not fit to be imployed in the Church, nor trusted by the State. But what they are God knoweth, and the World may know if they pleaſe to conſult their Writings, and to examine their Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their Tenents. They are not, to them that know them, what they are reported by, and to them that know them not. I ſeldom ſee any of them, very ſeldom converſe with them, yet I know them ſufficiently to make me bewail their condition, and the vast dammage to thouſands of Souls, not in the out-skirts alone, but very Heart of <hi>England,</hi> by their Excluſion and Suppreſſion; who are both able and willing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the everlasting Interest of precious Souls, which are committed in the mean while, in many parts of the Land, to them that neither can nor will. If a Husband-man have more Land than he can Till, much of his Land must lie Fallow and yeeld no profit; if a Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man have a great Harvest, and diſcharge his Labourers, he will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer loſs. It is a ſmall Pariſh indeed that will not find a pretty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrious Man work enough: There is enough for us, and for them to do, if there were the greatest <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Minds, and wiſest diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions, according to each Mans Abilities.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb facs="tcp:50217:5"/>
               <hi>5.</hi> I have ſometimes taken heart to vindicate what may be juſtified in them, out of a juſt reſpect to the Common Faith, and Proteſtant Religion; and there is no more objected, nor worſe things imputed to them by Proteſtants, than Papiſts impute to us all: If I have no courage to plead for them, ſo far as their Cauſe will bear it, I may prove a Coward in mine own Cauſe; Every good Man ought to be true to Truth, and the common Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> Not to revile nor provoke them that differ from me. If I have deſcribed any Perſons of an impoſing perſecuting temper, with any meaſure of ſeverity: if there be no ſuch Perſons, it is a miſtake, and no injury; if there be ſuch, Writing is Painting, I have fitted my Colours to the Face, I have not repreſented any ſowrneſs of Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but what I ſaw upon it. Let us all entertain Peace, and give it place to rule in our Hearts; ſeek Peace and purſue it, and pray for the Peace of Jeruſalem. <hi>Farewel.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>The Reader is entreated to excuſe the <hi>Errata,</hi> the Author being abſent from the Preſs. Theſe few the Printer hath obſerved, <hi>viz.</hi> Page 5. read <hi>Paſce.</hi> P. 11. l. 22. r. <hi>As, that many Miniſters are poor.</hi> P. 20. l. 21. r. <hi>Nonconformity.</hi> P. 27. r. <hi>that maintained a Neceſſity.</hi> P. 28. l. 37. r. <hi>Fort.</hi> P. 29. l. 39. r. <hi>concluded</hi> P. 30. <hi>the words of</hi> Calfnill <hi>ſhould have been in the Margent.</hi> P. 62. l. 28. r. <hi>Squama.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50217:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Compaſsionate Repreſentation of the preſent Caſe and Condition of the <hi>Non-conformiſts, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am a Chriſtian, and therefore a Member of the Body; and as ſuch, am obliged by the Law of Chriſt, and excited by his Grace, to endeavour the Growth, Perfection, and Unity of that one Body; and according to the meaſure of Grace and Life received, I cannot but feel the pain of Diflocations, Wounds, Weakneſs, Exciſion, Sickneſs, or Suffering of any Part or Member of it. If I have any Faith or Love, I cannot but pray for the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Miniſters above all Chriſtians muſt have Salt in themſelves, and be at peace one with another: they muſt preach the Goſpel themſelves, and rejoice that it is preached by others, tho otherwiſe-minded; and all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians muſt pray that the Word of the Lord may have a free courſe, and be glorified.</p>
            <p>I have ſome feeling of the broken ſtate of the Church of God in this Kingdom: but, alas! how little do I feel? how unfit am I to move thoſe that have healing Hands, and ſtore of Ointments, to heal our Wounds? If I could but open the Caſe of a Church for many years in pain, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered of her Burden, groaning to bring forth Unity and Peace, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not: followed long with ſtrong Convulſions, that it is a wonder ſhe hath not died in every Fit; I might move the compaſſions of her Phyſicians, to hold a Conſultation to expedite her Cure. Many of her Sons have of late bemoan'd her; and ſome have made enquiries into the Cauſes of her Ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but their Compaſſions have done themſelves more good than her. She is not at all the better for their trouble for her; ſhe is as ill at eaſe as at any time, in a waſting, complaining, declining ſtate. And to ſay the truth, there are many that make ſad Complaints of her Paſſion, Harſhneſs, and Severity; They ſay, that ſhe procured the turning of many of her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters out of their Maſter's ſervice; that ſhe is not kind to her own Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but locketh up her Bread from them, or appoints Stewards that do not faithfully diſpenſe unto them, but ſell their Bread, and put the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50217:6"/>in their own pockets. And thoſe Stewards for ſmall Wages hire under-Officers, that feed them but once a day, moſt commonly with that which coſts them but little. And that ſhe is ſo ſevere, that all that ſerve her, muſt put in Bonds for more than they can pay, and ſubſcribe to impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities; and, in ſhort, they ſay, ſhe uſurps authority over her Husband. They ſay, they can ſerve him, but cannot pleaſe her; they can ſerve him, and die for him, but cannot live in the ſame Houſe with her.</p>
            <p>For my part I will ſay no ill of her, nor make bate between the Bride and the Bridegroom; I am honoured to be a friend to him, and indeed I cannot be his friend, and not hers. But this, I'le rather ſay, that ſhe hath taken ſome ill courſes, and no good courſes for her own peace; ſhe hath been led, and abuſed by ill Inſtruments about her, and is indeed changed from what ſhe was in former times, and is not ſo kind and tender as ſhe was wont to be, by report of many that knew her heretofore. I am ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſorry for her. O that I could give her eaſe! I am no Phyſician my ſelf; but a ſorry Meſſenger may run and call the Doctor, and beſeech him, that if he have any bowels or tenderneſs of heart, he would make haſte and apply all his skill to ſave the Life, and reſtore the Health of the Mother of many Children, who will fall into the cruel hands of Pope and Devil, ſo ſoon as her eyes are cloſed. O how they long to hear of her Diſſolution! O what a ſick and divided Houſe do I live in! I cannot take reſt in my Soul for the Contentions of my dear and loving Maſter's Wife; I cannot lie dry in my Bed for the continual dropping: My Pilgrimage and courſe for theſe many years, hath been moſt uncomfortable unto me for the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual dropping in a rainy day. The Contentions are grown notorious, all our neighbours know them. 'Tis a moſt divided Houſe! I have no heart to make repetitions, of what I have read and heard to paſs between my dear Mother and my dear Brethren; between my Brethren amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the fellow-Servants. It is a ſhame that the World ſhould know it! But it cannot be hid: our very Enemies laugh among themſelves, and hope to turn us all out of doors, and get poſſeſſion. They have been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting, ſtating of Caſes, petitioning, pleading, and appealing to the Judgment-ſeat; that my heart akes to think of theſe things. I have prayed for Peace, and have denied my ſelf, to pleaſe my Mother. I will not find fault with her; my Soul longs for peace, and if I might prevail, I cannot tell what I would do, on condition that her Servants that have been turned out, may be taken in. But becauſe I cannot ſee how this will be without an Order of the Juſtices of Peace, I will humbly repreſent the Caſe as truly as I can, and intreat their Order for a ſpeedy ſettlement of my diſplaced Brethren. The Complaints are grievous. The Mother com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of the diſobedience of her Children, they will not be ruled by her:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50217:6"/>ſhe would have them to be all of her mind, and uniform. She is a Godly Woman indeed, and keeps Prayers morning and evening in her Houſe; and ſhe is earneſt to have them Aſſent and Conſent to all and every thing contained in a certain Book, and uſe no other. Some of them do not love to be impos'd upon, and think they are of thoſe years, as to know how to pray, and plead a Promiſe from their Maſter, of his holy Spirit to aſſiſt them. In the diſcharge of any Impoſed Form (but others can ſubmit to that, if that would do) She would have them wear white Linen, wide Sleeves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> kneel when they eat and drink at the Lord's Table; and will have all their Children baptized, and alſo croſſed in the forehead, which if you would ſee, is not to be ſeen, for indeed it vaniſhes as ſoon as made. For theſe things ſhe pleads Authority in her Self, and from her Supreme Governour upon Earth. Since her Marriage with Kings, ſhe is grown wealthy in Eſtate. The Woman that was ſometimes in the Wilderneſs, drawn before Magiſtrates, caſt into Priſon, that was forced to hide her head in Conventicles in thoſe nights of old, (that for many Ages ſpake a hard language, wore a triple Crown, went in gorgeous Apparel, of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies upon Ceremonies, carried in pomp, (Princes did kiſs her feet) that adorn'd her Walls with Tapiſtry and Images; grew Imperial in making Laws, and gave her mouth to Curſing and Bitterneſs.) I ſay, ſhe now can ſhew her face, that was ſometimes forced to hide it, and is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Reformed and Chaſte; but having Lordſhips and Preferments to beſtow, ſhe hath been rather like a Domineering Miſtreſs, than gentle Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as ſome of her Children have complained of her; and hath rather ſuted her ſelf to the Mode of Earthly Kings, than the Will of her Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly King and Husband. It cannot be denied but that ſome have been ambitious of her Favour, and for the Preferments which they have got by their Ceremoniouſneſs, have done her no good, and to get up above her fellow-ſervants, have ſet her above her ſelf. And for ought I ſee, theſe ambitious covetous Perſons have been evil Inſtruments of great Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Differences with her Children; and they alſo having a ſpice of <hi>Adam</hi>'s nature, and growing ſtomachful, with their Reaſon, could not bear a Superiority among Equals, and ſeeing they were Children of the ſame Father, knew no other difference than for Prudential Government, a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority of Order, or the Honour of Seniors; but not a Superiority of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and Power.</p>
            <p>The more powerful Houſe (for, alas! they have divided Houſes) that they may make Laws and govern others, do attribute great Authority to the Church; indeed as great as Jeſus Chriſt her King and Husband had: as if when he aſcended into Heaven, he gave among his other Gifts, even all that he had himſelf, to his Church and Spouſe. One R. R. a Writer that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50217:7"/>profeſſed to much intimacy with her, as to undertake to give her Senſe, and Reaſon of her doings, doth aſſert her Power and Authority to be twofold; <q>As all other Bodies Politick, the one of Juriſdiction to correct and reform,<note place="margin">Preface before his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Canons, &amp;c.</note> by Spiritual Cenſures, to preſerve the Churches Purity, and reduce to Unity the Troublers of the Churches Peace, not by Arguments alone, but Spiritual Cenſures, even to caſting out of the Church. The other, a Power of Legiſlation, to make Canons and Conſtitutions. For tho our Great Lord (ſaith he) hath already gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to his Church moſt holy and wiſe Rules and Laws for the ſame purpoſes; yet becauſe they are general, and there may ſome doubts and controverſies ariſe about their meaning, it doth neceſſarily follow that there muſt be an Authority left to this Church, and Governours there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to make new Laws upon emergent occaſions, to determine particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities,</q> (where by the way obſerve, that from a Power to reſolve the Doubts that may ariſe about the Sence and Meaning of thoſe General Laws of Chriſt, he gets ground by ſtealth, even to infer a Power to make <hi>new Laws</hi>) <q>and there muſt be a definitive Sentence of Superiours to decide Doubts and Controverſies. He argues both from the reaſon of the thing, and that Chriſt gave this Power, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.21, 22. <hi>As my Father ſent Me; ſo ſend I you.</hi> And one particular of Juriſdiction there expreſſed; <hi>Whoſe ſoever Sins ye bind on Earth, they are bound in Heaven.</hi> The Legiſlative power of making Laws and Conſtitutions for regulating Manners, and determining Controverſies, cannot be denied to be granted in that large Commiſſion;</q> 
               <hi>As my Father ſent me, ſo ſend I You, &amp;c.</hi> (Where again obſerve how he grows upon us, from a Miſſion to a Commiſſion. They are ſent indeed, but their Commiſſion is no other than to go, when ſent.) Yea in the next ſentence he ſaith, our Lord commiſſions his Apoſtles, (ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that pag. 1.) he defines the one Holy Church, to be the Society of Believers to whom that double power was given; but here it is given to the Apoſtles: (Have the Society of Believers the ſame power the Apoſtles had? or, doth the Commiſſion given to the Apoſtles, impower the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Believers to do as they did?) <q>He commiſſions the Apoſtles (ſaith he) with the ſame neceſſary ſtanding Power that he had, and <hi>exerciſed as a mans for the good of the Church:</hi> this is a Commiſſion in general for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Laws; Then in particular, for making Articles, and Deciſions of Doctrines, controverted Power is more explicit and expreſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>All Power is given unto me: Go ye therefore, and teach all Nations;</hi> that is, with Authority. And what is it to teach with Authority, but to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and oblige all people to receive the Truth ſo taught?</q> When I read ſuch Diſcourſes, and ſuch Conſequences, I do leſs wonder that they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50217:7"/>who are given to ſtrong Deluſions, do ſee thoſe dazling Wonders; <hi>in Tu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es Petrus, &amp; ſuper hanc Petram;</hi> or, that ſee the two Swords committed to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> in, <hi>Paſſe Oves meas,</hi> when he was only appointed to be a carefull Shepherd, <hi>Paſſe Oves meas?</hi> But ſome Men are perſpicuous, and have Eyes to lead others (that want Eyes of their own) and can ſee as clearly into a plain Text, as a Prieſt can into the bottom of a <hi>Papiſt's</hi> Heart, by his All-<hi>ſeeing Ear</hi> in Auricular Confeſſion.</p>
            <p>Others do build their Towers and Caſtles upon other Texts, which I paſs by. — Thus for the ample power of the Church. The power which Chriſt hath given to her I revere and acknowledge.</p>
            <p>Others go another way to work, and lay the ſpecious Towers and Battlements of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> upon the King's Supremacy; affirming two things: 1. That the Modes required, are things indifferent. 2. That the chief Magiſtrate may make Conſtitutions about things indifferent.</p>
            <p>And ſome upon one, and ſome upon another ground, do raiſe a great Duſt, Contention, and Diſcontent: ſome quarrel not, but are of a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and peaceable diſpoſition, and wiſh for Peace and Concord: but theſe are quarrelled with for their Moderation. And truly it is an ill ſign of an aſpiring contentious nature, in thoſe that will fall out with Peacemakers, that are ſober and moderate, and wiſh that both contending ſides may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand one another better, and love one another more, and remove the matter of debates and ſtrifes. How are the Ejected called! it grieves my heart to hear them called all to naught: and how are theſe names retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? And many throw Bones of Contention among them; whiſper, and backbite, and carry tales, to ſoment the heats, which gentle tempers labour to cool.</p>
            <p>The other broken Party of the diſſatisfied and complaining Family, are not ſo well agreed as it were to be deſired; but they differ more in Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentals than Subſtantials from one another, I mean the Brethren whoſe cauſe I attempt to open. Some of them will conſent to an impoſed Form of Prayer, and all to Decency and Order, as neceſſary in Chriſtian Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies; and, in a word, to all that is contained in the General Rules and Laws of Chriſt, and rationally deduced from them, as far as they do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand. They all ſubmit to an Epiſcopacy of primitive Inſtitution and Limitation, with the due Exerciſe of Diſcipline; and they that cannot agree to the ſame Form of Government, are for maintaining Peace and Love under different Forms, and they yeeld enough to have made them Miniſters in the Apoſtles days, and after. They ſay, 'tis true, that to us there is but one Lawgiver, and that is Chriſt; and they will teach what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he hath commanded them: They hold that his Laws are ſufficient
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50217:8"/>for the Government of the Church; that the Church muſt be ſubject to Chriſt; that her Power, as <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Writers have maintained, is only Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial under Him; that all Power is ſeated ſtill in Him, and not made over by Him to any other; that the Churches Power is not deciſive, (for as ſuch they argue, that Controverſies have not been decided, by any that here ingroſſed the name of the <hi>Church</hi>) but declarative, and ſo far binding, as the Reaſons are cogent and divine. They acknowledge the King's Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, as it hath been declared by former Learned Writers againſt the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Antagoniſts, and Uſurpers of that Sovereign Right: [as by <hi>Nowel</hi> againſt <hi>Dorman, Rainold</hi>'s conference with <hi>Hart,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> and many more.] They aſſert a Liberty which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath given them, and cannot ſubject themſelves, as the ſervants of men, in the things of God.</p>
            <p>They offer to aſſent to all the Eſſentials of the Chriſtian Faith, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all the Ordinances of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and every part of his Worſhip, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and Order in the Worſhip of God, as was ſaid before; and, in ſhort, do ſay, Shew us but what the Apoſtles Rule was, and we will walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it, and, as far as we have attained, be of one mind, and walk according to the ſame Rule.</p>
            <p>But then, they can never yeeld to declare an unfeigned Aſſent and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to Laws, Rubricks, and Ceremonies, that are ſignificant of any Grace, or obligatory to any Duty of the Covenant of Grace, or to make Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies federal Signs, tho not Seals; nor the Reading the <hi>Apochrypha,</hi> and Neglecting <hi>Canonical Scripture,</hi> and other things, which divers of them have ſpoken of at large, and cannot be repeated in this place. They pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, and we believe them, that they quarrel not becauſe they may not be Lords and Biſhops, or that others are ſo promoted; they declare it is no grief to them, if the Magiſtrate, or legal Patrons, beſtow the Revenues of the Church upon whom they pleaſe, and are legally qualified according to the Conſtitution. They only beg the uſe of that Liberty of their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, to preach and worſhip God according to the Primitive Rule, and Simplicity; and that they may not be Ejected and Excommunicated, and forced to beg their Bread, becauſe they cannot conſent to what <hi>they cannot believe,</hi> nor vow againſt their Duty.</p>
            <p>The danger of giving them a Toleration, while they remain Diſſenters, is ſtrongly ſuggeſted, from the multiplication of <hi>Papiſts, Socinians</hi> and <hi>Jews,</hi> as the effect of the Toleration in the <hi>Netherlands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But two things may be replied: 1. Widen the Terms, which may be done with ſafety to the Church, and there will be no need of a Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they will be incorporated with us. 2. There can be no ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from Chriſtians of the ſame Faith, and ſubſtantial Worſhip, but of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Accidental Modes, as from <hi>Socinians, Papiſts, Jews,</hi> of a contrary
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50217:8"/>Faith and Worſhip. And why we cannot be as kind and liberal to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, indulging a Liberty to them in ſmall things, as we are to <hi>French, Dutch,</hi> and to <hi>Lutherans,</hi> I do not know.</p>
            <p>I have repreſented the Diviſions of this moſt famous Church of Chriſt, not with the exactneſs of an Hiſtorian, nor of an Arbitrator, or a Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, but as beſt ſuiting with a Man in haſte, and trouble. And, here's enough to move the honeſt and faithful Juſtices to arbitrate Differences, and command the Peace. Nothing elſe will do, nor any other Man ſo likely to compoſe the Difference as they. For Prayers innumerable have been made to God; who acts by means in ſettlements of Peace and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: therefore we muſt pray Men too. The different Parties will not agree. The Commiſſioners<note n="*" place="margin">in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> an. <hi>1662,</hi> commiſſioned by the King.</note> diſputed, <hi>and both carried the Cauſe.</hi> The Ejected humbly peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned the Biſhops for Peace; they would not hear them. And what Arguing, Preaching, Writing hath been ever ſince! Some Reverend Sons of the Church, in love to Peace, and fear of Enemies, have earneſtly called and exhorted the Diſſenting Ejected Brethren to come and unite, to come into the Preſent Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as ſafeſt, as ſtrongeſt, as beſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But if they could not come in at the Narrow Door, eighteen years ago, and the Door as narrow ſtill as it was then, and there be the ſame Croſs-bars laid acroſs, as were then, to keep them out, to what purpoſe is the Exhortation? Is there a great Storm a coming? they think that Chriſt is the ſame Ship, and they are as ſafe as any other. They may clearly plead, they could have conformed at firſt, upon better worldly terms than now; they might have ſaved what they have loſt, and got their ſhare with others: to come now to conform, when all places are full, and not enow for numerous Expectants, and when there is nothing for them without tedious waiting; and if their Judgments and Conſciences could not enter then, how can they now? Unleſs their Heads have voided all their Reaſons, and ſo are grown leſs, or that Cuſtom hath made the Entrance ſmoother for them. Learned and Worthy Men have written for and againſt, and are they gained over to one another? If they are, it is more than they will confeſs. The one writes <hi>the Miſchieſ of Separation;</hi> the other denies the Charge and Proof; and another throws back the Miſchief, a Miſchief of Impoſitions: and many Swords are drawn by Seconds, too many bitter words for the Children of the ſame Heavenly Father, that are called to One, even to the One Hope of their Calling. The one writes, <hi>You are guilty of Schiſm:</hi> and the other ſays, <hi>Who made it?</hi> — My Bowels, my Bowels! <hi>O thou the Prince of Peace, make Peace in thine own Houſe, Family, and Kingdom;</hi> make of theſe twain, one Body, and let there be no Schiſm in it: as they are made One Body, in One, the ſame
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50217:9"/>Breaſtplate of Faith, in the ſame Girdle of Truth; ſo let them be ſhod with the Shoos of the Goſpel of Preparation of Peace, and let not one hinder another to run, but cauſe both to walk in the ſame path, to put on Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and to have the ſame mind that was in thee. —</p>
            <p>Methinks it were but fit for us, who weekly petition our good Lord to <hi>deliver us from all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs, from all falſe Doctrine, Hereſie and Schiſm,</hi> out of a Spirit of Love (if the Peace of God rule in our Hearts) upon our knees to petition our Governours for our Brethrens enlargement, and reunion with us, that they may not lie under the Cenſures and Reproaches of open Sinners, nor lie under the Imputation of Schiſm, and other ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicions, and be the ſubject of Scorn to every <hi>Papiſtical Scribler,</hi> and many other Miſchiefs and Slanders: But there being no hope of that, let every Man do his part for healing of the Breaches. And therefore I cannot but ask my Superiours Pardon to handle a tender point indeed, even to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend the Caſe of my Reverend Brethren the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> to the good Opinion, and charitable thoughts of them that can help with one Act to decide, what a thouſand Volumns cannot. I would not, if poſſible, be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtood, I am for Unity and Conformity, but not ſuch an Uniformity as hinders Unity, by turning the Church into a Party. I am not a partial <hi>Hyper-aſpiſtes,</hi> they can beſt manage their Cauſe, as beſt knowing their own mind, neither have they been wanting to it; Nor ſhall I give my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church an unbeſeeming word; but yet between the Judicious, Holy and Peaceable part of Fathers and Brethren of it, and the Faction<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making Aſpiring-party, I cannot but diſtinguiſh. Indeed theſe call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>[the Church],</hi> but by monopolizing the Church, and ingroſſing the Goods of the Church if they could; they have no greater ſhare of the Spirit of the true Catholick Church, than their deſpiſed Brethren, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> by them. Theſe are <hi>ſupra,</hi> or <hi>Tranſ-Conformiſts,</hi> that keep the Rule of Conformity much as they do their Reſidence. Theſe Men are <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> too, as I could ſhew in ſome conſiderable particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and are a <hi>Rubrick</hi> to themſelves. But my buſineſs is not to accuſe them; but ſeeing the moſt are <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> either above or under the Rule, (a Rule, if ſtrictly kept at all times, in all Offices, where were a man's Prudence? and if a Man hath no Pruderce to uſe, or may not uſe it, he is very unfit to be a Miniſter in the Church of God.) I am for the calling of more <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> into the Company, and for making <hi>Non-conformiſts Conformiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our bleſſed Saviour, in the Parable, compares himſelf to an Houſholder going a far Journey, that gave authority to his Servants, and to every Man his work, and commanded the Porter to watch; and when he went, he left Peace as a Legacy; <hi>My Peace I leave with you.</hi> But, alas! how few have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50217:9"/>ſought to get and keep that Legacy, or to do their Work? We may with Sorrow look into it, and find it, in his Abſence, a moſt broken and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Houſe. In it we ſhall find two ſorts of Children, all by the ſame Father, but not as if all of a Mother: The elder and the greater combine, make a mighty Party, and they even rule the Mother. Theſe have the beſt of every thing, and ſnatch what the others had, or ſhould have, and part all as they pleaſe among themſelves, and uſe their poor Brethren no better than if they were Baſtards. Theſe complain, and entreat, and beg: but if they beg, they are not regarded; if they complain, they are peeviſh and diſcontented, deſerve nothing, or no better than to be turned out of doors; if a Man pities them, and pleads for them, he is one of them. — The greater ſay, Theſe peeviſh whining Children are diſobedient to our Mother, vex her Bowels out, hinder all Government and Uniformity; if it were not for them, how happy would it be with us! But who can tell, but the great Ones may fall out among themſelves? The Ejected have written, pleaded their Cauſe, drawn up their Caſe, and petitioned, but to what purpoſe? To as much as a Man that hath a good Right to a part of an Inheritance, but poſſeſſed by an elder Brother, who thinks he can preſcribe for all, and plead Poſſeſſion and Law; beſides that, his Friends being Judges in the Court have given it him: This poor younger Brother has but a weak Purſe, and few Friends, and what doth he but remonſtrate, open his Caſe to many, and to his elder Brother, with humble Entreaties? But becauſe he doth not go to Plow, or go a begging, or to ſome Corners of the Land, or go to ſome Forreign Plantation, he is rated as a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Fellow, factious, and querulous, and knows not what he would have. Poſſeſſors are deaf to Petitioners. He that would recover his Right muſt go to Law for it, or loſe all, except a little Alms, and that as pure Kindneſs, without pretence of Right or Deſert.</p>
            <p>There were a Company of Juſtices that ſate long upon the Bench, and theſe firſt made an Order for Miniſters to come in Bond to certain Duties, or elſe they diſcharge the Pariſhes of them, and turn them out of doors. Many hundreds refuſed to give in their Bonds, upon which they were turned out of their Houſes and Pariſhes; and by an after-Order, they were not to come within five Miles of any Corporation, that ſent Burgeſſes to Parliament, or of their own laſt Abodes; forbidding them thereby any Employment in Corporations, to get their Livings, or the Charity of their former good Neighbours, if they had any. Theſe and their Families are up and down the Nation, indeed, no better eſteemed, which is a ſhame to tell, than Vagrants, by too many, yea, unfit to live.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as they may be very uſeful, it would be an Act worthy your place, to move the Honourable Bench of Juſtices, that never liked
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50217:10"/>that rigorous Order, in Mercy and Juſtice to take the Caſe of theſe eject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Miniſters to conſideration, and by another Order to capacitate them to dwell and labour in any City, Town Corporate, Village, and Pariſh whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any thing in any Law or Statute to the contrary notwithſtanding. I make bold to preſent theſe following Particulars to you, with Truth and Charity.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Their Sufferings.</item>
               <item>2. The Hardneſs of their Caſe.</item>
               <item>3. The Reaſonableneſs and Equity of many of their Deſires and Propoſals.</item>
               <item>4. Qualifications, and worth of their Perſons.</item>
               <item>5. Their Behaviour.</item>
               <item>6. The Concluſion.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. Their Sufferings. And they admit of various Aggravations, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their various Circumſtances. Some of them were Fellows of Colleges, and not otherwiſe preferred, in the heat of their Studies; and thereby, together with their Preferments and Livelihoods, loſt what could not be recompenced to them, their Opportunities for learned Studies, and their Increaſe of Abilities, which is an ineſtimable Loſs to any good and ſtudious Man. It was a Trial to ingenuous Men, to be turned out of their Fellowſhips, (their little Regalities) and become Chaplains or Schoolmaſters, for ten or twenty Pound <hi>per annum.</hi> And there is a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in a Man's Entertainment, when he is courted and invited into a Family, or Employment, and when his Neceſſity drives him; and his Entertainment looks more like a Courteſy, than a Reward, with Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and Acknowledgment.</p>
            <p>Others had but a little Time of Settlement in their Country-Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to lay up any thing for themſelves and Families. The more conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encious the Miniſters are, the more apt to marry young, chuſing rather to caſt themſelves double upon the Providence of God, than ſin in a ſingle Life; honeſt Marriage being honourable, tho attended with honeſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty. And the moſt of their Ejectors, being ſingle Perſons, and having eaten the Cream of Preferments in their riſing Times, had little conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration towards great and ſmall Families. Indeed as many as had treaſured up Faith in God, and his Promiſes, had enough to hold out their Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage: But if God was ſo kind, as to give them Faith to live by, they were unkind, that would force them to that noble kind of Life. If God had given them Grace, care ſhould have been taken to find them Work. But God did not caſt them out of their Work, nor out of his Care: He became their Patron whom Men ejected, and preſented them, ſome to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50217:10"/>Places always vacant, dark, and neglected; and others he preferred from Country-Villages, to Towns and Cities. One Inſtance comes into my Mind, of Mr. <hi>Edward Lawrence,</hi> of <hi>Baſce</hi>-Church in <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> (a worthy Preacher) turned out with a Wife and many Children, who being asked how he did intend to live, made Anſwer, <hi>The ſixth Chapter of</hi> Matthew <hi>muſt maintain me, my Wife and Children, and it is enough for us all,</hi> or words to this effect, (it is many years ago ſince a worthy Perſon told me the Story) and ſo he found it true: And being driven out of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try by the Rigors of ſome Men, his double Ejection, the firſt out of his Pariſh, the ſecond out of the Country, made way for his Settlement in <hi>London,</hi> whither he was forced. And ſuch Reaſons as theſe may be given, why many of the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> reſort to <hi>London,</hi> and other Towns, which is imputed to them by ſome as a Fault of Ambition, or worſe.</p>
            <p>Others, how far ſoever grown in Years, and deſirous of Reſt in the Work of Chriſt, muſt out of their quiet Quarters, <hi>colligere Sarcinas,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move their Beds, and be gone, and ſell their Books. And what many of them have ſuffered ſince, is not my part to aggravate. God hath taken care of many, and given them Food and Raiment, and Work at their Peril and Coſt. And others, beſides the Hardſhips of Impriſonments, Chargeableneſs of many Removes, have lived by their Induſtry, by their Labours, even of their hands, a very hard and pinching Life, as I doubt not, is very well known to many of all Qualities, and that many Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in the Church are very poor. It is not well taken by ſome, that they ſhould complain of their Sufferings; and may be not well taken from me, to relate what I know and have heard of particular Perſons, to whom with their Children, caſt Suits have been acceptable, to cover and adorn them.</p>
            <p>I know it is objected, that many live better than ever they did; <hi>get Hundreds</hi> per annum, <hi>keep Coaches,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, I do not think there is any <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> in the Land, but will quit what they have for what they had, without ſeeking Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for Loſſes. 2. If ſome that can graze upon a bare Common, have a little Fleſh, and ſome Wooll upon their Backs; others have waſted their Patrimonies, and real Eſtates. 3. It is their Wiſdom to ſet the beſt Face on't, to ſhew they are not diſcouraged in their Conditions, that they may not appear to beg as they go along, to keep themſelves from Contempt, and other prudential Conſiderations. 4. I wiſh ſome had better Feet and Legs, than to be carried in Coaches; I am glad they can keep, hire, or borrow, whatever others are.</p>
            <p>Others may object the Sufferings of the Royal Party, and many worthy Divines, into whoſe places many of the now Ejected violontly entred.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50217:11"/>
               <hi>Anſw. Mercurius Ruſticus</hi> ſaith enough to make a Man's Heart bleed. I would not diminiſh thoſe Sufferings, by enlarging theſe; I am ſorry for both, for either: But if I may uſe my Freedom, without offence to any, in this afflicting Point, I humbly offer: 1. It is probable, that many hundreds the now Ejected were not Men in thoſe evil Days, therefore not guilty. 2. There was a Proviſion of a fifth part for the Wives of the Ejected then, there is none for theſe. 3. Who can anſwer for the Violences and Injuſtice of Actions in a Civil War? Thoſe Sufferings were in a Time of general Calamity, but theſe were ejected, not only in a Time of Peace, but a Time of Joy to all the Land, and after an Act of Oblivion, when all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be reconciled, and to be made Friends, and to whoſe common rejoycing theſe ſuffering Miniſters had contributed their earneſt Prayers, and great Endeavours. Many Miniſters in the Church are poor, in poor Livings, in poor Curacies, yet are preferred above or equal to their Merits: many are poor through their Prodigality, and ſuperfluous Wigs and Habits. Many Men of worth are kept low, by reaſon of Pluralities, and Engroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, that live at eaſe, that had not a Heart to labour, nor give the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers their Hire. Theſe are Grievances that call for Redreſs.</p>
            <p>It is objected, That they ſuffer through their own Faults, they ſuffer for Diſobedience to a Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> I do earneſtly interrogate, Can either thoſe that voted for that Bill, or they who uſed all Power and Art to procure thoſe Votes to paſs it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Act, ſay from their Conſciences, That it was Conſcience towards God that obliged them to it; that if they had not put into the old Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, the new Additions, they had ſinned againſt Jeſus Chriſt, and their Faithfulneſs to him? If they can, then I query, if that be not an erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Conſcience? And then the Queſtion ſo often thrown upon the <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> of the Obligation of an erring Conſcience, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted upon the Impoſers, by indifferent judicious Men. If they cannot ſay ſo, then they might put the Queſtion to their own Souls, Whether they have not ſinned in impoſing, or procuring ſuch things to be impoſed, as tend to the temporal Hurt and Ruine of many Families, and the great Detriment to the Church of Chriſt, if not by the Loſs of the publick and profitable Labours of many able Miniſters, yet by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions that have broken in upon us by theſe Impoſitions, and their deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubmiſſion to them? It nearly concerns Governors of the Church, to weigh the Neceſſity of their Impoſitions, as it doth others to weigh, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they may act, or refuſe to act according to them: For if they rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly extend their Power beyond the Lines, to the hinderance of the Goſpel, they ſin againſt Chriſt. Caution and Tenderneſs muſt therefore be uſed. If all theſe things, and every one of them, be neceſſary to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50217:11"/>enjoined and practiſed, for the Peace, and Union, and Edification of the Church of God, then they condemn their Predeceſſors of Omiſſion of what was neceſſary, and contradict what they declare concerning ſome of theſe things, that they are alterable, and indifferent in themſelves, and may be altered. And if ever any Time ſince their Impoſition might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Change of them, or laying the Ceremonies aſide, that Time when they were anew enjoined, and now when they are required, might excuſe it, for many Reaſons that are ready at hand.</p>
            <p>Again, ſome ſay, It is their Fault that they ſuffer. But who muſt be Judges of that? Their own Conſciences, or they who cenſure them? They are as confident it was not their Fault, but their Duty, and roundly write,<note place="margin">Of this after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</note> either they that impoſe, or they that refuſe, ſin grievouſly; and plead their Forbearance as no Sin, but a Duty. O moſt unhappy Conteſt and Strait! when either Party muſt grievouſly ſin againſt God. Certainly our bleſſed Law-giver Chriſt never made ſuch a Law, as tends in the execution of it, to the Hurt of any of his Subjects and Miniſters, or to ſtop the Encreaſe and Progreſs of the Goſpel: And who can juſtify any particular Law, or Condition of Communion, that is but a Stumbling-block in the way of any, that are paſt being Babes, and otherwiſe inſtructed to his Kingdom?</p>
            <p>I conclude with this Obſervation, That the general Rules of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, were given to accommodate the Differences between Jews and Gentiles, to end the Strife, to give eaſe to the Conſcience, ſilence their uncharitable Cenſures, and heal their Breaches about things indifferent; and not to determine for one againſt another, with Penalties. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> was grieved to ſee the Tranſgreſſion of a Ceremony to be more ſeverely reprehended, than the Tranſgreſſion of God's Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſaith Reverend Mr. <hi>John Lloyd,</hi> in his <hi>Treatiſe of Epiſcopacy,</hi> pag. 53. But this is not a place to diſpute. Can any of the Impoſers take the Comfort of their own Impoſitions, and ſay, they have Peace and Comfort in the things for which learned and holy Men do ſuffer? Or if it were to do again, I would do no leſs? Then all I'le ſay more is this, Then bleſſed Act of Uniformity! which brings Comfort to them that made or procured it, and to them that ſuffer by it alſo! Comfort from the Cauſe of other Mens great Sufferings, and the great Loſs to Souls, muſt be rare indeed.</p>
            <p>Conſider theſe Sufferings of the Ejected. They ſuffer really in their outward Eſtates, in their Freedoms, in their Dangers, (being obnoxious to the Canons, as far as to Excommunication, to the Temporal Laws,) in their Names and Honours, as counted diſobedient, factious, fanatical, are the Objects of Virulence and Dirt, and are repreſented as intolerable
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50217:12"/>Theſe are great Sufferings, and a ſafe way to be redreſſed, is worthy the Wiſdom and Tenderneſs of Authority. <q>I am ſure, ſaith the Learned Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> it is contrary to the Primitive Practice, and the Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration then uſed, to ſuſpend or deprive Men of their Miniſterial Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for not conſenting to Habits, Geſtures, and the like.</q> 
               <hi>Iren. p.</hi> 64. <hi>Rule</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Then next let me conſider what the Caſe is; and if it will appear to be a hard Caſe, it calls for the more ſpeedy and effectual Relief: And this is the next thing I humbly offer to prove.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Caſe of the ejected Miniſters is really a hard Caſe.</p>
            <p>And I will endeavour the Proof of it in two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Shewing what is required of them.</item>
               <item>2. The Penalties for not doing what is required.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The things required of them are either,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Eccleſiaſtical.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Political,</hi> and mixed with a Caſe of Conſcience, in the two Declarations they are bound by Law to make.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt; The <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Part of their Subſcriptions and Declarations; (For brevity ſake I will paſs the old Conformity.) <hi>They are bound to declare their unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That this is a heavy Injunction in it ſelf, tho abundance of us have made little of it; for ſome good Teeth can eat the hardeſt Cruſt, but it is Cruſt for all that. It is hard for any Man,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To aſſent and conſent to any thing of another Man's Opinion and Judgment, except firſt he that gives the Aſſent have as throughly ſtudied, and doth as clearly perceive the things, as he doth that requires the Aſſent. To aſſent to ſome things will not paſs in this caſe, it muſt be all and every thing. What Parliament-Man will aſſent to any Bill, except he firſt be ſatisfied in the reaſon of it? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or, 2. Except he that requires the Aſſent and Conſent, have a degree of Infallibility, or be endowed with an abſolute uncontroulable Power, againſt whom no Scruple, no Objection, or Debate, can or ought to be made.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Would not every Practitioner in Phyſick think it hard, that he muſt ſubſcribe Aſſent and Conſent to all and every thing contained in, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50217:12"/>bed by the <hi>London</hi> Diſpenſatory, and uſe no other? Would not the Judges in the Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> think it hard to declare their Aſſent and Conſent to all and every thing in the Statutes and Laws of <hi>England,</hi> and not endeavour any Alteration? And why is it not hard for us, to ſubſcribe to all and every thing contained in a Book of Divine Worſhip, not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by a Divine infallible Spirit? Can more be required to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or cleareſt Point of Doctrine or Faith?</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is hard, as appears by the Qualifications and Mitigations of the Sence of the Declaration. If the Words were clear, and eaſy for the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and Will to digeſt, there needed no ſoft Conſtructions to help them down. It coſt all, that are careful what paſs their hands, ſome thoughts to make them eaſy. And had it not been for that one word, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> and the help of that, it would have ſtuck with many, that are as great Pillars of the Church as any in it, in their ſtations and degrees. That which is eaſy and plain, will eaſily paſs with an ordinary Underſtanding. The various Conſtructions of the Forms are impartially given by the Reverend Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nonconformiſts Plea for Peace, <hi>p. 158, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> I ſhall not run out to defend either the rigorous or milder Conſtructions, but ſhew that the Caſe of Diſſenters is hard, and indeed of all Conformiſts, that muſt take the Words without <hi>Salvo</hi>'s, or elſe muſt fall under the Cenſure of Hypocriſy, and doing more Hurt by conforming, than if they had not conformed. It is hard to lay the Streſs of many Parts of a Declaration, as fully and diſtinctly expreſs'd, as the Wit of ſevere Men could word them, upon one general word, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> It is a hard Conſtruction of affirmative Propoſitions, or Parts of a poſitive Declaration, to be explained in a privative or negative Sence; yet ſo we find them ſmoothed, and rolled up in Liquoriſh, that they may paſs the narroweſt Throats. I ſhall take the Pains to tranſcribe two Conſtructions, of two excellent Men, which may be taken next to a publick Sence and Conſtruction, eſpecially the one of them, who was the moſt learned and rarely tempered, Biſhop <hi>Reynolds,</hi> in his Sermon of Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration before the Houſe of Peers, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 7. 1666. a Day of Solemn Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation for the Peſtilence, <hi>pag.</hi> 24. <q>And truly it is an Honour which Learned Men owe to one another, to allow Liberty of Diſſent in Matters of meer Opinion, <hi>ſalvâ compage Fidei, ſalvo vinculo Charitatis, ſalvâ Pace Eccleſiae,</hi> (for theſe three, Faith, Love, and Peace, are ſtill to be preſerved;) ſo it is a Charity which good Men owe to one another upon the ſame <hi>Salvo</hi>'s, to bear with the Infirmities of each other, not to judg, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, or ſet at naught our Brethren; <hi>as uſeleſs and inconſiderable Perſons:</hi> But whom God is pleaſed to receive into his Favour, not to caſt them out of ours. This Latitude, and Moderation of Judgment, ſome learned
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50217:13"/>Men have taken the freedom to extend, even to the Caſe of Subſcriptions by Law required. The learned Author of the Book called, <hi>An Anſwer to Charity maintained;</hi> and the late learned Primate of <hi>Armagh,</hi> Arch-Biſhop <hi>Bramhall;</hi> (and quotes their Words in the Margent, which are theſe) <hi>For the Church of</hi> England, <hi>I am perſuaded, that the conſtant Doctrine of it is ſo pure and Orthodox, that whoſoever believes it, and lives according to it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly ſhall be ſaved; and that there is no Error in it, which may neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate or warrant any Man to diſturb the Peace, or renounce the Communion.</hi> This in mine Opinion is all intended by Subſcription. — The Words of the Arch-Biſhop are theſe; <hi>We do not ſuffer any Man to reject the Thirty Nine Articles of the Church of</hi> England <hi>at his Pleaſure, yet neither do we look upon them as Eſſentials of ſaving Faith, or Legacies of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; but in a mean, as pious Opinions, fitted for the Preſervation of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity: Neither do we believe any Man to believe them, but only not to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict them.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This Sermon being printed upon requeſt of the Lords, I thought this moderate Expoſition of Subſcription, (as it was aimed at by that rare Preacher, I believe) might paſs for approved by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and be next to a legal authentick Sence of all things required by Law: For if Subſcription of Articles be in ſo laxe a Sence, much more to ſome of the other things. But Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who hath as good reaſon to know as any one Man, hath daſhed this Conceit; for he writes, that when the Lords would have put in this Proviſo, <hi>To the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Book,</hi> the Houſe of Commons refuſed it, and the Lords acquieſced in their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons given in at a Conference about it. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ſupra,</hi> p. 160.</p>
            <p>The other Expoſitor of our Declaration, which I ſhall produce, is the Reverend Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, who ſhines as a Star in our Firmament, and in regard of his own great Reaſon, and Acquaintance with other great Mens thoughts, may direct the Courſe of fluctuating Coaſters, that look for a ſafe Landing-Place, and ſure footing, before they proceed in the Service of the Church. In his late contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Sermon,<note place="margin">Miſchief of Separation,</note> among other ſharp Reflections upon his Friend, Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> he hath theſe words, <hi>pag.</hi> 49. <hi>It is a hard Caſe with a Church, when Men ſhall ſet their Wits to ſtrain every thing to the worſt Sence, to ſtretch Laws beyond the Intention and Deſign of them, to gather together all the doubtful and obſcure Paſſages in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendars, Tranſlations &amp;c. And will not diſtinguiſh betwixt the Approbation of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, and of the Choice of things; for upon ſuch Terms as theſe Men think to juſtify the preſent Diviſions. I much queſtion, whether if they proceed in ſuch a manner, they can hold Communion with any Church in the Chriſtian World.</hi> So far he. From which Words I make bold to infer, (and if I
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50217:13"/>am too bold, I do ſeriouſly ask his pardon.) 1. It ſeems to me that he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits the ſence of the Declaration of <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent,</hi> to the ſcope and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Law, which is <hi>to the uſe</hi> of the Book, and all things in it. 2. That a Man may aſſent and conſent <hi>to the uſe</hi> of thoſe things, which a Man would not, or doth not <hi>chooſe,</hi> if left to his choice and liberty. 3. Here is a Blot caſt by his Elegant Pen, at leaſt upon ſome of the things, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in, and preſcribed by the Book, as things not to be choſen, but only to be uſed by conſtraint. 4. An Impeachment againſt the Contrivers and Exacters of Conformity, for requiring Aſſent and Conſent <hi>to all and every thing</hi> (not making a difference) contained in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which ſuch Excellent Men as the Dean is would not uſe, if left to his choice, nor any other wiſe man chooſe; and ſo their meaning comes to this: I will uſe this Book, (and all things to be uſed in it) ſuch as they are, inſtead of better; and tho not declaring our Aſſent, is puniſhable with Deprivation, or Non-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance into the Publick Miniſtry of the Church, and the loſs of a Man's Livelihood, and Temporal Rewards of the Miniſtry. 5. If our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours ſhall from their great Wiſdom and Compaſſion to a moſt divided Church, alter the terms of Communion and Conformity, and unlace the Garment which is made too ſtrait for the Body, which faints, being ſtraitly laced: then no Man muſt be offended with the Reverend Dean, or any other that conformed in this large ſence, if they diſuſe the things now in uſe, and fall in with ſuch things as may like them as well or better. 6. I infer, and retort (which is to my purpoſe) that it is a hard Caſe with a Church, when Men ſhall ſtrain their Wits to frame Declarations, under ſuch ſevere penalties, to paſſages that are doubtful and obſcure, and capable of an ill ſence, that we muſt turn to Kalendars to find out Leſſons in the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> that have Canonical Leſſons enow, to uſe other Tranſlations than the laſt and beſt, &amp;c. But Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> doth inſtance in other things, as well as <hi>Kalendars and Tranſlations,</hi> and holds occaſional Communion with the Church as it is, and would much rather, if thoſe paſſages, (which the learned Dean calls <hi>doubtful and obſcure</hi>) were not impoſed, and is Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick enough to hold Communion with any Chriſtian Church, that hath not corrupted the Eſſentials of Chriſtian Worſhip.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Declaration and Subſcription contains Matter Political and mixed, which is, <hi>Not to take up Arms, &amp;c.</hi> a thing eaſily conſented to. I do confeſs that there have been fair Explications and Limitations pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed to make this gain Aſſent: but yet it is hard, unleſs all men could attain to the ſame ſence, and thoſe Explications are not known to abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance that ſubſcribe and declare, and ſo promiſe and ſwear in the dark: I am confident many never read the Covenant that renounce it, and ſo renounce they know not what; and may take their Informations from the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50217:14"/>Pulpit, where a Thread-bare Jingle hath been of late much uſed by ſome, of the Holy-League in <hi>France</hi> (to root out the Proteſtants) and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League, which muſt be taken to be as bad as that, being coupled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with it. But that which is hard in theſe things is, 1. To renounce what many do not know, (and moſt never took) nor was ever like to he impoſed, but to expire with the Men that took it, in the heat of War: [But the Time of the Expiration of this Part draws on.] 2. Not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it our ſelves, but to declare that no Man elſe is bound. How can I judg of another Man's Obligation in his <hi>Place and Calling?</hi> &amp;c. Beſides, admit I declare that there lies no Obligation upon any other Man, any more than upon my ſelf, yet it is but my Opinion: I think he is not obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, but my Opinion doth not abſolve or releaſe him that thinks himſelf obliged, and all this while I do really renounce but for my ſelf. And it is hard for any Man to determine a Caſe of Conſcience, whoſe Caſe he doth, it may be, not well underſtand, and may fail in the ſtating of it.</p>
            <p>But I muſt not deſcend into Particulars, neither do I determine againſt it, but only tranſiently ſhew the Excuſableneſs of them who cannot declare theſe things, (altho they do not refuſe it from any Principle of Diſloyalty or Faction) and that from this undeniable Conſideration and Argument: That which all the Art, and Wit, and Intereſt of ſome Men in great Place and Power in the Houſe of Lords, could not make to paſs, but was oppoſed with that Clearneſs, and Cogency of Reaſon and Reſolution, as if they were ſaving a Nation, by reſiſting the Teſt, which could not paſs into a Bill, muſt needs be hard to be impoſed upon Miniſters. And it is not improbable, but that noble Oppoſition gave the greateſt Repulſe to a dangerous Deſign, long carried on to ſubvert the Government, under a Pretence to preſerve it as it is, in all its Parts and Circumſtances. And the joint Oppoſition of ſome Popiſh Lords againſt the Teſt, doth not at all abate the Strength of this Reaſon; for they having a cruel Deſign, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of this Frame, could not chuſe but oppoſe a Teſt, which was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to preſerve it unalterably as it is, both in reſpect of the Perſons that govern in the Throne, Church and State, and in its preſent Conſtitution. And whereas many things have been carried on, as tho to prevent the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of ſuch a Year as that unhappy <hi>Forty one;</hi> yet really there have been great Endeavours uſed, to bring us under the Obligation which ſome brought upon us in the Year <hi>Forty;</hi> I mean the <hi>Et caetera</hi> Oath, leaving out the <hi>Et caetera</hi> it ſelf, and under a colour to preſerve us from a Long Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of the Complexion of <hi>Forty one,</hi> Proteſtation, and Covenant, and War, gave Umbrage to a fearful Plot, to bring us under a Papal Slavery, introduced by bloody Maſſacres. And who talk'd more of <hi>Forty one,</hi> than ſome that are of late diſcovered to be Traitors, and having profeſſed to be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50217:14"/>Sons of our Church, committed Fornication with <hi>Rome,</hi> who had almoſt gone out her full Time, ready to be delivered of a Pope, and had called the <hi>Midwife</hi> and many Ladies to the Labour, beſpoken Nurſes and Goſſips, and Choice of Fathers, to <hi>Antichriſten</hi> the Monſter with the Name of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, with all the Ceremonies of the Maſs? Some of the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> being willing to declare their deteſtation of Diſloyalty, were taken with the Declaration ſent out after the <hi>Oxford</hi> Oath, or <hi>Five<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile Act,</hi> being made believe that that Explication was ſent forth by good Authority; yet many ſmelling what was intended, were reſolved to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their own private loſs of Liberty, by aſſerting the Publick Liberty, and (as things now appear) the Government ows them a kindneſs; and the Noble Lords and Commons (that underſtood themſelves, and the encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Perils) immortal thanks for their ſeaſonable Activity to preſerve the ſtrong and ancient Government. But, to conclude this Head, It is not kind, to ſay no worſe, to engage all Miniſters, never ſo young, or elſe they cannot enter into the Churches Miniſtry, either to be Politieians, to ſtudy State-Affairs, (for which many have been extreamly blamed) or elſe to be led as Fools, into they know not what. And they that have given this further Teſt of their Loyalty, have little cauſe to take it well; as if the ſtanding Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy were not tye ſufficient to keep us honeſt, but diſhonour us by a ſuſpicion of Diſloyalty and Treachery. Obſerve the method of proceeding; firſt they began with us, as Guides of the People; and next proceeded to draw in Corporations, and from thence to impoſe it upon the Parliament it ſelf; to which if they had ſubmitted, we ſee what would have followed, We might have ſeen ſuch Commiſſioned by the King's own Authority,<note place="margin">See the Commons Anſwer to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Meſſage about Tangier.</note> as would have deſtroyed His Perſon, and cut all our Throats, having firſt tied our Hands. Thus I have ſhewed what is required from them. The ſecond Particular follows.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Conſider the Penalties to be inflicted upon ſuch as will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They who were in the Miniſtry muſt be divorced from thoſe, whom they had baptized, and eſpouſed to Chriſt, among whom they had laboured; and their remove was to the ſhaking of many Chriſtians, and to the great harm of the Church. I will inſtance only theſe three ways. Firſt, it was as bad to many, as the change of a Nurſe to a weakly Child. (I will ask no Pardon for the Compariſon, it being Apoſtolical.) 2dly, It was enough to make many ſtagger, and call in queſtion all thoſe Truths that had bin delivered to them, ſince that their Preachers are judged unfit to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in Truſt with Souls: and tended to breed much Atheiſm, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50217:15"/>Errors. 3dly, It tended to alienate the minds of many from the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church, that would enforce Laws binding to many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary things, even to the Ejection and Deprivation of many Orthodox and painful Divines. And this ſticks with many to this day; by which the Church-Rulers have not got, but loſt. And theſe things aggravated with an imputation of Diſhoneſty in Miniſters, by the publication of their Aſſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the full Congregation. For if any had diſtinguiſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſubſtance of Ordinances, and Accidentals, which was but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to many people, (who thought no Worſhip Divine without the Common-Prayer,<note place="margin">See alſo Mr. <hi>Blake,</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant ſealed. p. <hi>308.</hi>
               </note> (as I my ſelf have known) nor any Child rightly baptized without the Croſs) yet by this Act of Uniformity they muſt declare Aſſent and Conſent to all and every thing, to Croſs as well as Baptiſm, to Ceremony as well as Subſtance. And how eaſie was it for ſinful people and weak, to ſay, See what theſe Men can do — Yea, in caſe that in any after-time, wiſe and moderate Governours ſhould ſee a neceſſity of making Alterations: Then again, teaching Scorners to ſay, Yea, ſee what theſe Men can do — to the great diſhonour of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and diſgrace of the beſt of Miniſters. And one would think that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Courts continue to ſwear Churchwardens to preſent, they had Spies enow upon our <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> and Puniſhments ſmart enough, they might have ſpared to require this Declaration; or, if they had thought us honeſt, our promiſe to conform had been ſufficient, tho kept in the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and made at our Inſtitutions. Yet through this Diſhonour we attain our Honour. They are debarred from all exerciſe of their Miniſterial Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, their Wives and Children turned out of doors; and when they had made a ſad and chargeable Remove of late, muſt remove again upon the Five-mile Act. And theſe Penalties were next to Death, and I conceive proved the Death of many. I remember the Renowned Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> wrote theſe words to the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> and deſired them earneſtly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Cenſure of the Apoſtle's <hi>Wo</hi> being ſo dreadful: <q>I ought not to eſteem any thing a juſt Cauſe, why I ſhould wilfully incur the Cenſure of Silencing my ſelf from Preaching, for which I ought not as willingly to adventure my Life.<note place="margin">The General Defence of the three Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. Part <hi>1. p. 163.</hi>
                  </note> The <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts</hi> have ſuffered what is next to Death, and too many have ſuffered even unto Death, in Priſons, where ſeveral caught their Death, and others died: (it is a dreadful ſtory) of whom ſhall their Deaths be required?</q> And it is eaſie to retort thoſe words of the Reverend Biſhop, <q>Impoſers ſhould not eſteem any thing a juſt Cauſe of bringing any under the cenſures of Silencing of Preachers from preaching, for which they may not adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to take away their Lives.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50217:15"/>
It is objected, <hi>That they ſin againſt the Law.</hi> And they may anſwer, <hi>Who procured the Law?</hi> it is the Magiſtrate's Sword, but who moved him to draw it? They are told they have no cauſe to complain of Sufferings, for the Magiſtrate hath been merciful, and hath not execued the Laws.</p>
            <p>Thanks be to God for the Mercy: but all have not been ſo merciful as the King hath been, or many inferiour Magiſtrates; but their Mercy hath not been kindly taken by many, who ſhould have more tender bowels than any Man that wears a Sword. To conclude; A reaſonable Underſtanding may judge that Law not fit to remain in force, that is not fit to be put in execution. That Law cannot be good, that is not fit to be brought to act, without more real hurt than good. And if the wiſe and merciful God hath by many remarkable Providences put a ſtop to their execution, it is time for Men to annul the Law.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Penalty is hard upon them that make their offers to be admitted into the Churches Service, or that would come in but for theſe Injunctions. It is but a narrow paſſage that is made for them that enter in: yet what ſhall they do who have ſpent all they have in a Preparatory Education? In they muſt, tho but to a Curacy, (which is not eaſie to be had.) It is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to think with what Implicit Faith they do what is to be done; yet muſt Aſſent to more than ever many have ſtudied, [rather following Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple than Reaſon] or elſe there is nothing for them to do. Others that are enclin'd to Learning, and to ſerve in the Goſpel, are deterred upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny accounts, and have great prejudices againſt Conformity, becauſe of the great reverence they have to <hi>Nonconformiſts;</hi> and theſe are under a great temptation to perpetuate a Nonconformity: which is more ſutable to their inclinations, as being a ſtate of freedom to their Conſciences, from great Bonds and Obligations, tho an Eſtate attended with hazard to their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Eſtates. And all young Students are under this neceſſity, either they muſt ſubſcribe hand-over-head, or elſe they muſt ſpend their time in theſe endleſs Controverſies of the Church, and be engaged in the dolefull and fearfull Wars of the Church, on one ſide or other.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third Conſideration that pleads for our <hi>Non-conforming Brethren,</hi> is taken from the Reaſonableneſs of their Demands. I diſtinguiſh theſe Demands, into thoſe Propoſals made by the Commiſſioners in the <hi>Savoy, Anno</hi> 1662, with that Modeſty, Gravity, Humility and Reaſon, treating the Biſhops and other Commiſſioners as Superiours. 2. Into thoſe which have been repeated by particular Perſons, and may be ſeen in the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of Laborious and Catholick Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Corbet,</hi> and Dr. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen</hi> in his learned and moderate Book of Church-Peace, Love, and Unity. I ſhall only generally compare what they humbly deſired, with what was declared;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:50217:16"/>
1. In his Majeſties gracious Declaration concerning Eccleſiaſtical Affairs: a moſt large and healing Plaiſter for the Churches Wounds; and might have been a Pillar to have born up the Church in Unity, as his Gracious <hi>Act of Indempnity and Oblivion</hi> hath held up the State; if ſome Men, who can be loyal for their own ends, had not (perhaps) bin induſtrious to make Diviſions by their Affected Terms of Union.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They humbly moved, but for what great Men, and famous in the Church of God to all poſterity thought fit to grant. In that Year 1641, there was a Committee for Religion appointed in the Houſe of Lords, ten Earls, ten Biſhops, ten Barons. The Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln (Williams)</hi> ſent a Letter to ſome Divines to attend that Service (who met in his Houſe,<note place="margin">Breviat of his Life. <hi>p. 24.</hi>
               </note> the Deanery of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>) upon which Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> hath this Note: <q>Upon the whole matter, I believe this Committee will prove the Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Synod of <hi>England,</hi> to the great diſhonour of the Church: and what elſe may follow upon it God knows.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Divines were no leſs Men, than the moſt Venerable Arch-Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> Biſhop <hi>(Williams)</hi> of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> Dr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> (after Biſhop of <hi>Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>) Dr. <hi>Brownrig</hi> (after Biſhop of <hi>Fxeter</hi>) Dr. <hi>Ward</hi> (Profeſſor of Divinity in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and Arch-Deacon of <hi>Taunton</hi>) Dr. <hi>Featly,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hacket,</hi> of late Biſhop of <hi>Coventry</hi> and <hi>Litchfield.</hi> All theſe ſubſcribed a Paper called, <hi>The Proceedings, &amp;c. touching Innovations in Doctrine and Diſoipline of the Church of</hi> England; <hi>together with Conſiderations upon the Common-Prayer Book.</hi> Out of which I draw a Parallel, with the Propoſals of the Divines appointed to treat by his Majeſty's Commiſſion, with the Archbiſhop and Biſhops, and other Divines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> at the <hi>Savoy.</hi> [See Account of the Proceedings, printed <hi>Lond.</hi> 1661.]</p>
            <div type="considerations">
               <head>The Divines appointed to meet in the Dean's Houſe, <hi>1641.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Conſiderations on the Common-Prayer.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether the Reading of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> Sentences of Scripture, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring in divers places in Hymns, the <hi>Epiſtles</hi> and <hi>Goſpels,</hi> ſhould not be ſet out in the New Tranſlation?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether Leſſons of Canonical Scripture ſhould not be put in the Kalendar inſtead of the <hi>Apocrypha?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:50217:16"/>
5. That the <hi>Doxologie</hi> ſhould be always printed at the end of the Lord's Prayer.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Whether the <hi>Rubrick</hi> ſhould not be mended, where it is, (that the Leſſons ſhould be ſung in a plain Tune) why not, read with a diſtinct Voice?</p>
               <p n="7">7. Whether <hi>Gloria Patri</hi> ſhould be repeated at the end of every <hi>Pſalm?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſider.</hi> 9. Whether the <hi>Hymns, Benedicite, Omnia Opera, &amp;c.</hi> may not be left out?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether the <hi>Rubrick</hi> ſhould not be mended, where all Veſtments in time of Divine Service, are now commanded, which were uſed 2. <hi>E.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="10">10. In the Prayer for the Clergy that phraſe perhaps to be altered, <hi>[which only workeſt great marvels.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>In the Rubrick for the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Lord's Supper.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Alteration to be made, that ſuch as intend to Communicate, ſhall ſignify their Names to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat over Night, or in the Morning before Prayers.</p>
               <p n="12">12. The next <hi>Rubrick</hi> to be clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, How far a Miniſter may repulſe a ſcandalous and notorious Sinner from the Communion.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:50217:17"/>
13. Whether that <hi>Rubrick</hi> is not to be mended, where the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens are ſtraitly appointed to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Alms for the Poor, before the Communion begins, for by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience it is proved to be done bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when the people depart.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Whether the <hi>Rubrick</hi> is not to be mended, concerning the party that is to make his general Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon his Knees, before the Communion, that it ſhould be ſaid only by the Miniſter, and then at every clauſe repeated to the people.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Whether it be not fit to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert a <hi>Rubrick</hi> touching kneeling at the Communion; that is, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in all humility with the Prayer which the Miniſter makes when he delivers the Elements.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Whether in the firſt Prayer at the Baptiſm, theſe words, <hi>Didſt ſanctify the Flood</hi> Jordan, <hi>and all other Waters,</hi> ſhould not be thus changed, <hi>Didſt ſanctify the Element of Water?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20. Whether it be not fit to have ſome diſcreet <hi>Rubrick</hi> made to take away all Scandal from ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying the Sign of the Croſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Infants after Baptiſm, or if it ſhall ſeem more expedient, to be quite diſuſed; whether this Reaſon ſhould be publiſhed, that in Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Liturgies, <hi>No Croſs</hi> was conſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Party, but where Oil alſo was uſed; and therefore Oil being now omitted, ſo may alſo that which was concomitant with it, the Sign of <hi>the Croſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:50217:17"/>
21. In private Baptiſm, the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick</hi> mentions that which muſt not be done, That <hi>the Miniſter may dip the Child in Water, being at the point of Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="22">22. Whether in the laſt <hi>Rubrick</hi> of Confirmation thoſe words be to be leſt out, <hi>[and be undoubtedly ſaved.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23. Whether the Catechiſm may not receive a little more enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="24">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:50217:18"/>
24. Whether the Times prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited for Marriage are quite to be taken away?</p>
               <p n="25">25. Whether none hereafter ſhall have Licenſes to Marry, nor be asked their Baues of Matrimony, that ſhall not bring with them a Certificate from their Miniſters, that they are inſtructed in their Catechiſm.</p>
               <p n="26">26. Whether theſe words in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony <hi>[with my Body I thee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip]</hi> ſhall not be thus altered, <hi>I give thee power over my Body?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="27">27. Whether the laſt <hi>Rubrick</hi> of Marriage ſhould not be mended, that the new married Perſons ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Communion the ſame day of the Marriage, may it not well be; or upon the next <hi>Sunday</hi> following, when the Communion is celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</p>
               <p n="28">28. In the Abſolution of the Sick, were it not plain, to ſay, <hi>I pronounce thee Abſolved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="29">29. The <hi>Pſalm</hi> of Thankſgiving of Women after Child-birth, Were it not fit to be compoſed out of proper Verſicles taken from divers <hi>Pſalms?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="32">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:50217:18"/>
32. In the Order of the Burial of all Perſons, 'tis ſaid, <hi>We commit this Body to the Ground, in ſure and certain hope of Reſurrection to eternal Life:</hi> Why not thus, Knowing aſſuredly that the Dead ſhall riſe again.</p>
               <p n="34">34. In the Litany, inſtead of <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, and all other deadly Sin;</hi> Would it not ſatisfy thus, From Fornication, and all other grievous Sins.</p>
               <p n="35">35. It is very fit that the Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the Meeter, in the Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Pſalms</hi> ſhould be mended; and then lawful Authority added unto them, to have them publickly ſung before and after Sermons, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times inſtead of the Hymns of Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Evening Prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:50217:16"/>
               <head>The Commiſſioners in the <hi>Savoy, 1661.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In regard of the many defects which have been obſerved in that Verſion of the Scriptures which is uſed throughout the Liturgy, —We therefore deſire in ſtead thereof the New Tranſlation allowed by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, may alone be uſed. 8. p. 5.-9. It is therefore deſired that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing may be read in the Church for Leſſons but the Holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:50217:16"/>
                  <hi>Exception</hi> 3. We deſire that the words, <hi>For thine is the Kingdom</hi>—may be always added to the Lord's Prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Except. p.</hi> 13. The Leſſons, and Epiſtles, and Goſpels, being for the moſt part neither Pſalms nor Hymns, we know no Warrant why they ſhould be ſung in any place; and conceive that the diſtinct reading of them with an audible Voice, tends more to the edification of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Excep.</hi> We deſire it may be uſed but once in the Morning, and once in the Evening.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Except.</hi> We deſire that ſome <hi>Pſalm</hi> or <hi>Scripture-Hymn,</hi> may be appointed inſtead of that <hi>Apocryphal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Except.</hi> We deſire it may be left out.</p>
               <p>The Prefaces of many <hi>Collects</hi> ſeem not to have any clear and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial reſpect to the Petitions, <hi>&amp;c. Partic.</hi> p. 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Order for the Lord's Supper. Except.</hi> The time here aſſigned (in the <hi>Rubrick</hi>) for notice to be given to the Miniſter, is not ſufficient.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Except.</hi> We deſire the Miniſters power, both to admit and repulſe from the Lord's Table, may be, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Majeſty's Declaration, <hi>Octob.</hi> 25. 1660.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:50217:17"/>
                  <hi>Except.</hi> Collections for the Poor may be better made at, or a little before the departure of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants.</p>
               <p>We deſire it may be made by the Miniſter only.</p>
               <p>We deſire that the following <hi>Rubrick</hi> in the <hi>Common-Prayer Book</hi> of 5. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. may be reſtored, for the Vindication of the Church, in the matter of kneeling at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It being doubtful whether either the Flood <hi>Jordan,</hi> or any other Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, were ſanctified to a Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal uſe by our Saviour's being bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed:— We deſire this may be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe expreſſed.</p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>General Propoſal.</hi> After ſtrong arguing, they conclude, We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt earneſtly entreat the right reverend Fathers and Brethren, to whom theſe Papers are delivered, as they tender the Glory of God, the Honour of Religion, the Peace of the Church, the Service of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, in the accompliſhment of that happy Union, which his Majeſty hath ſo abundantly teſtified his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of, to join with us in impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuning his moſt Excellent Majeſty, that his moſt gracious Indulgence, as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50217:17"/>to theſe Ceremonies granted in his Royal Declaration, may be continued and confirmed to us and our Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, and extended to ſuch as do not yet enjoy the Benefit thereof.</p>
               <div type="exception">
                  <head>Of Private Baptiſm</head>
                  <p>We deſire that Baptiſm may not be in a private place at any time, unleſs by a lawful Miniſter, and in the preſence of a competent num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and where it is evident that any Child hath been ſo baptized, no part of the Adminiſtration may be reiterated in publick under any li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitations, and therefore we do not ſee any need of any Liturgy in that Caſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="exception">
                  <head>Exception of Confirmation.</head>
                  <p>Altho we charitably ſuppoſe the meaning of theſe words was only to exclude the neceſſity of any other Sacraments to baptized Infants; yet theſe words are dangerous, as to the miſleading of the Vulgar, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we deſire they may be expun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="exception">
                  <head>Except. of the Catechiſm.</head>
                  <p>We deſire the firſt Queſtion may be altered, conſidering for 20 Years paſt, many had no God-fathers; and and the <hi>7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </hi> Q. The ſecond Anſw. Wherein I was viſibly admitted into the number of the Members of Chriſt. That the Commandments may be inſerted according to the laſt Tranſlation of the Bible. That in the Expoſition of the Commandments, ſome clauſe may be inſerted to refer to the fourth Commandment, that thoſe words be omitted. Anſwer, thus given, Two only, <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> &amp;c. A more full Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the <hi>Creed, Lord's Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Ten Commandments,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="exception">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:50217:18"/>
                  <head>Except. of the Form of Marriage.</head>
                  <p>The word <hi>Worſhip,</hi> being much al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in the uſe of it, ſince this Form was drawn up, we deſire ſome word may be uſed inſtead of it.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Rubrick</hi> doth either enforce all to forbear Marriage as are unfit for the Sacrament, or the unprepared to come to the Sacrament. And therefore we deſire it may be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the rather becauſe that Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age Feſtivals are too often accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with ſuch divertiſements, as are unſuitable to thoſe Chriſtian Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which ought to be before, and follow after the receiving of that Holy Sacrament.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="exception">
                  <head>Except. Viſitation of the Sick.</head>
                  <p>That form of Abſolution be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarative and conditional, as <hi>[I pronounce thee Abſolved]</hi> inſtead of <hi>[I abſolve thee]</hi> if thou doſt truly repent and believe.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Pſalm</hi> (121) ſeems not to be ſo pertinent as ſome other, <hi>viz. Pſal.</hi> 113. &amp; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128.—</p>
               </div>
               <div type="exception">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:50217:18"/>
                  <head>Except, Burial of the Dead.</head>
                  <p>Theſe words cannot in truth be ſaid of Perſons living and dying in open and notorious Sins.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="exception">
                  <head>Except. in the Litany.</head>
                  <p>In regard that the Wages of Sin is Death; We deſire that this clauſe may be thus altered, <hi>From Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and all other hainous or grievous Sins.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="exception">
                  <head>Gen. Propoſition, <hi>12.</hi> p. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Becauſe ſinging of <hi>Pſalms</hi> is a conſiderable part of publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, We deſire that the Verſion ſet forth and allowed to be ſung in Churches, may be amended, or that we may have leave to make uſe of a purer Verſion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="observations">
               <p>I ſhall not draw the Parallel any further, but infer theſe following Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That thoſe great and famous Men did ſee ſome neceſſity or reaſon for altering of many things in the Liturgy; and therefore the Presbyterian Divines, (moſt of whom were and are <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi>) were not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther captious and quarrelſom, they maintain'd a Neceſſity of Reformation. On the other ſide, there were learned Men who maintained there was no neceſſity of Reformation. But you ſee, againſt the ſenſe of thoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Divines that met in the Dean's Houſe, 1641.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I obſerve, That the Propoſals and Exceptions of the Commiſſioners in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> were not without great Preſident; and inſiſted upon many things, which the moſt eminent Fathers of the Church of <hi>England</hi> would have yielded to them, and doubtleſs much more, if not all, for Peace and Union.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To ſpeak a word for the reproached Brethren of the <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> (who are repreſented to have all the ill Humours of factious Perſons, and diſcontented, that know not what to ask, nor what they would have) is but a piece of Juſtice and Chriſtian Charity. Men think nothing but Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and Covenants, and Directory, will pleaſe them; which is not juſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50217:19"/>nor true. They deſired that the Liturgy may conſiſt of nothing doubtful or queſtioned amongſt pious, Orthodox, Learned Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Dr. <hi>Allen</hi> of <hi>Huntingdon-ſhire,</hi> and Clerk in the Convocation, did earneſtly labour with the then Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> (afterward Arch-Biſhop) that they might ſo refine the Liturgy, that no ſober Man might make Exception. He was wiſhed to forbear, for what ſhould be, was concluded on or reſolved. They deſired, the obſervation of <hi>Saints Days</hi> might be omitted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The moſt Reverend <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> and the reſt, begin their Conſiderations with this; <hi>Whether the Numes of ſome departed Saints, and others, ſhould not be quite expunged the Kalender?</hi> They deſired that there might be no ſuch Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Liturgy, as that the Exerciſe of the Gift of Prayer be thereby totally excluded, in any part of publick Worſhip. The moſt excellent <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.16.) and the reſt, recllon it among the Innovations; <q>By prohibiting a direct Prayer before Sermon,</q> and bidding of Prayer, (which is now the mode all over the Biſhoprick of <hi>Dureſm,</hi> as ſome that are no ſtrangers in it ſay.)</p>
               <p>They at the <hi>Savoy</hi> ſtood for a Reformation, and were not ſingular there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; for without it, the Reverend Dr. <hi>Featly,</hi> (a worthy Man, and great Sufferer in our unhappy Warrs, which is like the Sword that makes no difference) printed this Challenge and Manifeſto.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <q>The Articles of Religion need no Alteration at all, but only an Orthodox Explication in ſome ambiguous Phraſes, and a vindication a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt falſe Aſperſions.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <q>That the Government by Biſhops <hi>(removing all Innovations and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes in the execution thereof)</hi> is agreeable to God's Word, and a truly An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and Apoſtolical Inſtitution.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <q>That the Book of <hi>Common Prayer (N. B.</hi> the <hi>Kalendar</hi> being refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, in point of <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Saints and Chapters; ſome Rubricks explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſome Expreſſions reviſed, and the whole correctly printed, with all the Pſalms, Chapters, and Allegations out of the Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according to the laſt Tranſlation) is the moſt compleat, perfect, and exact Liturgy in the Chriſtian World.</q> 
                  <hi>Dippers Dipt,</hi> p. 16, 22. and <hi>Gentle Laſh,</hi> 1644.</p>
               <p>And this is the ſame in effect with what the Divines at the <hi>Savoy</hi> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly propoſed; and without all theſe Exceptions, that Champion, Dr. <hi>Feat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> would not undertake his Vindication of them: by which it ſeems the firſt of the Church-Conſtitution and Diſcipline was not tenable as it ſtood at that time; but our great Church-men were reſolved, that the World ſhould know their Strength, as well as Reaſon, to regain with advantage in 1661, what they loſt in 1641.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:50217:19"/>
The Presbyterian Divines (as they were called) did urge, both ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, heartily, and humbly, that the Ceremonies might be omitted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doubtful whether the Church had power to enjoin myſtical teaching Signs (which the Impoſers confeſſed indifferent) of no real goodneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which many of the Oppoſers accounted ſinful, others inconvenient, and unſuitable to the ſimplicity of the Goſpel; and had been, for a hundred Years, the Fountain of manifold Evils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And herein they were not ſingular; for other Men, when diſengaged, and Maſters of their Liberty, have ſaid as much, or enough to take off the edg, from Impoſers to require them, or of wife Men to deſire them. I ſhall here produce the Judgment of ſome learned and judicious Conforming Divines, concerning Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. The firſt ſhall be the moſt eminent Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> in that excellent <hi>Irenicum,</hi> the firſt born of his moſt learned Youth, and mature Reaſon and Judgment; and had it been the Work of his Age, it had been a Birth at full growth, in reſpect of Piety, Gravity, ſweetneſs of Temper, beauty of Complexion, wiſe Obſervations and Experience, that, <hi>and Author of the renicum,</hi> had filled up the Epitaph of the Dean of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> This is the laſt Propoſal of Accommodation; <q>That Religion be not clogg'd with Ceremonies.— Chriſtian Religion is a plain, ſimple, eaſy thing.— By Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies I do not mean here Matters of meer Decency and Order, for Order-ſake.—But Ceremonies properly taken for <hi>Actions figniſicative,</hi> their lawfulneſs may with better grounds be ſcrupled, <hi>pag.</hi> 67. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>pag.</hi> 66. We ſee the Primitive Church did not make ſo much of any uniformity in Rites and Ceremonies.</q>— I ſhall quote too much, if I give way to what is mature, and paſt his own mending, without diſparagement to his more grown Reaſon be it ſpoken.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is a great Scholar and Divine, the late worthy Mr. <hi>G. Lawſon,</hi> (Rector of <hi>Moor</hi> in <hi>Shropſhire</hi>) in his Expoſition of the Second Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Theopolitica, B.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <q>As for ſignificant Ceremonies, annexed to the Service of God, no ways conducing to the better performance thereof, I think they are better ſpared and omitted, than uſed and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. For tho conſidered in themſelves, without any reference to God's Worſhip, they be indifferent, and ſo in general may be lawful; yet if we examine their Original, the firſt occaſion of their Inſtitution; the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who uſe, or rather abuſe them, and underſtand withal how needleſs and unprofitable they be, and how offenſive to ſome weak Brethren; and alſo beſides theſe may be inſtituted many more of that kind, and may be impoſed upon the ſame ground; and that in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> they have been an occaſion of Superſtition: it muſt needs be included, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial and judicious Men, that they are not expedient. To ſay, and publickly declare that they have no ſanctifying Power, that they are
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50217:20"/>neither Holy nor Unholy, will not ſerve the turn: for the ſame may be ſaid of Images, at firſt, when they began to be uſed; and do what we can, many of the People do account them to be Holy, make them parts of God's Worſhip, and are more careful in the obſervation of them, than they are of the more weighty Duties of Religion. — [Doctrine in this caſe will not prevail, if the thing that they truſted to, be not taken from them. <hi>Calfhill</hi> of the Croſs, again <hi>Martial,</hi> p.88.]</q> 
                  <q>So it may be, bating the degrees of Offence, when Matters of Indifferency in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, are, by the generality of People not looked on as ſuch, but uſed as a neceſſary part of Divine Service.</q> Dr. <hi>Stilling. Iren.</hi> p. 64. They who induſtriouſly labour to keep out Popery, can never cleanſe a People from Superſtitions, while they keep up Ceremonies, an obſervation of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent uſe.</p>
               <p>My third Teſtimony is, a Man of great Learning, and of long ſtanding in the Church, Mr. <hi>John Lloyd</hi> B. D. now of <hi>North Tidworth</hi> in <hi>Wilts, Treat.</hi> of <hi>Epiſe. Liturg. Rites,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Lond.</hi> 1660. <q>Many have entertained a great fear, which hath alienated their Minds from all Epiſcopacy; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that innumerable company of unneceſſary and burdenſome Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies be inſeparable Concomitants of Epiſcopal Government. Indeed the fear is not vain, and without grounds, if we reſpect the degenerate Epiſcopacy, as it is, if we regard the Primitive, which hath been, and will be contented with a very few, if need be. — <hi>p.</hi> 32. S.15. (the whole Section gives a ſhort and full account of Primitive Simplicity). One Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why Ceremonies increaſed in the fourth Century, may be this, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Church more flouriſhed in proſperity than at any time before, and might be thought convenient, that the External Glory of the Church, ſhould be proportioned to the Glory of the Empire. <hi>p.</hi> 38. We may err, as in defect, ſo in exceſs of Ceremonies, or in the choice, or in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting and compelling others to own them for unchangeable Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Inſtitutes, or by too rigid preſſing of every of them, eſpecially upon People of weak Capacity, humble, peaceable, and ſcrupulous Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.—Antiquity is venerable, yet it may not, ought not continue a Rite or Ceremony in any Church, with whoſe Edification and Peace it is become inconſiſtent. There be but few Ordinances meerly Eccleſiaſtical, which have not in ſome Churches become noxious, or at leaſt uſeleſs. And there is a viciſſitude of Profit or Detriment growing from them in the ſame Churches, ariſing from notable changes in Perſons and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. — If it ſhould ſeem good to the Church of <hi>England</hi> to mend their <hi>Liturgie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">☞</note> or compoſe a new one, (if need be) more agreeable to the preſent Time, they ſhould do therein no more than the moſt famous Churches have done before; and which can be no diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50217:20"/>to the Wiſdom and Piety of the Compoſers of it, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended only to make it as fit as could be for the ſtate of the Church in their time, and not to frame and impoſe an Unchangeable Form, which could never prove incongruous to any poſſible variety in the ſtate of the Church; for this is not in the power of any perſons or Churches.</q> 
                  <hi>P.</hi> 54, 55. Thus far this great Student, modeſt, moderate good Man.</p>
               <p>I will content my ſelf with the Opinions of theſe three worthy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, when diſengaged; and altho they conformed, they were and are no doubt of the ſame mind, free in their minds, when obliged in their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice to ſubmit.</p>
               <p>What more than what I have ſhewed, the Commiſſioners at the <hi>Savoy</hi> pleaded for, may be ſeen in the Account of their Proceedings: But what got they by thoſe Debates beſides ſatisfaction in their own Souls, that they debated and petitioned for Peace? A very little indeed! And what the Biſhops gave with the one hand, they got with the other. It was ſtrange and hard that they could not prevail ſo far as to get the <hi>Commandments</hi> in the Church-Catechiſm &amp; Communion-Service to be after the laſt and beſt Tranſlation in our Bibles; but our Children muſt be taught the 4th Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment after the manner of the Judaizing Seventh-day-Sabbath Sect; for ſo they are taught, <hi>Wherefore he bleſſed the [Seventh day] and hallowed it;</hi> and our unwary People are taught to pray, that God would <hi>encline their hearts to keep this Law,</hi> that Law which enjoineth the Seventh-day as the Sabbath, which God bleſſed and hallowed: whereas the Law, <hi>Remember the Sabbath day,</hi> which extends to the <hi>Firſt day,</hi> as well as the <hi>Seventh day,</hi> and makes the Firſt day moral, when appointed by the Lord of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, (But this Doctrine was not conſonant to the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Thorndike,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hiſt. of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath. Juſt Weights &amp; Meaſures. Caſe of the Sabbath.</note> nor (which I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at) to the judicious Bp. <hi>Sanderſon</hi>) as much as the Seventh was from the Creation. What if an inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Child that is catechiſed, ſhould ask his Parent, What day do we keep as Sabbath? the Firſt hee'l ſay. But ſaith the Child, Why do we keep the Firſt? what Commandment for that? or what Promiſe? for we are taught in the Catechiſm, <hi>God bleſſed the Seventh day.</hi> Is not this a temptation to keep the Seventh-day Sabbath? Had the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> pleaded for that Tranſlation, they might have heard of their ignorance in the Hebrew: and demanding things not fit to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, they would not grant them, leſt they (as the <hi>Puritans</hi> have been miſrepreſented) ſhould Judaize in keeping the Holy Sabbath.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Doxologie,</hi> or concluſion of the Lord's Prayer, <hi>[for thine is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, &amp;c.]</hi> to be uſed always.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:50217:21"/>
Query. <hi>Whether they have not thereby taught us this Opinion, that tho Forms of Prayers are lawful, yet a variety is as lawful as a ſet form of words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We prove the lawfulneſs by our Saviour's Preſcription, <hi>When ye pray, ſay, &amp;c.</hi> And may we not prove a liberty, or a variety of expreſſions, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill to the ſame matter, when we read a difference in the ſame Prayer as delivered by two Evangeliſts, inſpired by the ſame Spirit? and when we ſee the practice of the Church is ſometimes to uſe, and ſometimes to omit the <hi>Doxologie</hi> and Concluſion? And why ſhall the Church ſo ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoin the exact uſe of all her Forms, and they who omit, (when their Prudence and Conſcience (as to ſome Prayers) tells them they ſhould ſometimes concerning ſome Petitions and Perſons) are liable to cenſure, when a part of the Lord's Prayer, as delivered by St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> is conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly omitted? For ought I ſee, a liberty and variety of Prayers, ſtrictly keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to divine matter, with abbreviations and enlargements, is as lawful as a ſtinted invariable Form of words, and is a matter of Chriſtian Liberty, to be uſed as ſhall beſt ſerve to the edification of the Church of Chriſt: and divers expreſſions are as much from the ſame Spirit (provided always they agree with the language of the Holy Ghoſt) as diverſities of Gifts, and conſiſtant with the Unity of the Spirit. And they who plead for a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Forms, muſt alſo yeeld to a variety upon the ſame ſubject, which we have for the King in the Service, and a few others.</p>
               <p>A Reformation was thought abſolutely neceſſary to Union. Hear what Mr. <hi>Herbert Thorndike,</hi> one of the Commiſſioners for the Church in the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> wrote; <q>But now that Unity is not to be had, without ſetling agreement in matters of Difference;<note place="margin">A due way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Differences; <hi>printed with his</hi> Weights and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. pag. <hi>236.</hi> Edit. <hi>1662.</hi>
                     </note> to propoſe what may ſeem beſt for the Community of God's Church, in the Cure of our Breaches, is not to give offence, but to take it away. Nor do I know any Man profeſſing the Reformation ſincerely, that could not wiſh with all his heart, that the whole Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Form to be ſetled, with the Circumſtance of the ſame, might be according to the Primitive Simplicity, and naked plainneſs of the Ancient Church. p. 245.— The form of Service now in force by Law, may be acknowledged capable of Amendment without diſparagement either to the Wiſdom of the Church that preſcribed it, or of the Nation that enacted it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Some promiſed much, but granted little; others begg'd more, &amp; pleaded hard, but obtained not. And may not this juſtify the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> waiting for, and earneſtly deſiring a redreſs of material things, ſince they could ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain but very little then, and cannot in conſcience ſubſcribe and declare now? If they had been gratified then, and had now been diſcontented without
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50217:21"/>more, there had been more reaſon for the prejudice that is propagated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
               <p>If it be objected, <hi>Why could not they have Conformed, as ſome of their Fellow-Commiſſioners did?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Anſwer; 1. Some very worthy Perſons did Conform, Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> Dr. <hi>Horton,</hi> Dr. <hi>Lightfoot;</hi> and after about ſeven Years ſilence, to the great loſs of <hi>Exeter</hi> College, <hi>Oxford,</hi> and the Church of God, Dr. <hi>Conant</hi> conformed, and theſe were all.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Reaſons why theſe did not, is, becauſe, as the ſame Spectacles will not ſerve all Mens ſight, ſo becauſe they could not, as they oft decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, both to the ſhaking off ſome, and the diſpleaſure of others within the Pale.</p>
               <p>My laſt Obſervation ſhall be upon the Perſons that managed that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate. The Commiſſioners that pleaded for the Union as it was, without a Reformation, were the ſtrongeſt and ſtiffeſt of any in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Men of great Learning, long experience in the Eccleſiaſtical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and that had ſuffered much, and were much exaſperated, as being (ſeveral of them next the Biſhops) moſt obnoxious to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as moſt guilty of Innovations in Doctrine and Diſcipline, by the Informations and Complaint of as Learned, and as great Men as any of them in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as may eaſily be produced out of the beſt account of thoſe Times; all except Dr. <hi>Morley,</hi> Dr. <hi>Earle,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> (againſt whom I remember no Complaints) and a few beſide. Their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and Sufferings, did recommend them to the King's Favour; and the great Agreement in their Perſuaſions, held them to one another; and having the diſpoſing of Preferments as they pleaſed, or at leaſt the Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of Candidates, Expectants complied with them, and were forward to walk according to their Meaſures. The moderating Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> was gone to Heaven; <hi>Prideaux, Brownrig,</hi> and others of another temper, and ſo it was eaſier for them to carry all their own way: and two things, as conducing to their deſigns, was neceſſary;</p>
               <p n="1">1. To frame a Convocation to their minds, and to that end, great care and pains were uſed to keep out, and to get in, by very undue Proceedings. Proteſtations were entred againſt all Incumbents not ordained by Biſhops, though it was not through their faults; and to exclude others, that they feared had any inclination to Moderation indeed, under the name of <hi>Presbytery.</hi> And ſuch an Election being made, as there was no great fear of calling any thing to free Debates, few leading Men being of another mind, ſo there were no Debates to ſpeak of; the greateſt that I could hear of, was between the <hi>Cambridg</hi> Profeſſor Dr. <hi>Gunning,</hi> and the <hi>Oxford</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor Dr. <hi>Creed,</hi> about (a hard Point indeed) <hi>the Age of Children to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:50217:22"/>
2. For all his Majeſty's moſt gracious and excellent Declaration, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, they laboured, by all their Intereſt and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, to have a Parliament that would paſs what they would contrive and prepare for them. And ſo they, inſtead of ſending more Labourers into the Vineyard, hired (as ſome ſay) Labourers to turn out, or keep out Labourers from entring in. And the Labourers in Penſion were not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed only in State, but alſo in Church-Work. Their Intereſt was ſo great in that Parliament, as to enact what was reckoned an Innovation in ſome Colleges in both Univerſities (by the above-named Biſhop <hi>Brownrig,</hi> and <hi>Prideaux,</hi> &amp;c. in theſe words, <q>By in trodu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Latin Service in the Communion of late in <hi>Oxford,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Copy of the Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>&amp;c. 1641.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation <hi>17.</hi>
                     </note> and into ſome Colleges in <hi>Cambridg</hi> at Morning and Evening Prayer; ſo that ſome young Students and Servants in the Colleges do not underſtand their Prayers.</q> But now the Latin Service may be uſed in any College, or Hall, in <hi>Oxford, Cambridg, Weſtminſter, Wincheſter,</hi> and <hi>Eaton,</hi> and Convocation of Clerks.</p>
               <p>The Commiſſioners on the other ſide, muſt be acknowledged Men of great and ſound Learning,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Tuckney,</hi> Dr. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> Dr. <hi>Conant, Horton, Lightfoot,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Woodbridg,</hi> Dr. <hi>Seaman,</hi> Dr. <hi>Spurſtow, Jacomb, Bates,</hi> &amp;c. and Biſhop <hi>Reynolds</hi> on this ſide.</note> and of more experience in the Paſtoral Office, and had converſed more with great Congregations than the others had, and ſo were more fit to Adviſe; as learned Practitioners in Phyſick are fitter to Adviſe, and more likely to hit the Temper of the Patient, than a Profeſſor in the Theory. And the account of their Proceedings will to Poſterity ſhew to the impartial and inquiſitive, both their Parts and their Temper. When I read them, I do the leſs wonder at what I heard,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bp</hi> S. <hi>at</hi> Stony-Strat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford <hi>in</hi> Bucks.</note> that a great Biſhop in his prime Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, ſoon after, did teach his Clergy againſt reading that Book.</p>
               <p>Thus was the Platform of the preſent Conſtitution drawn, and it ſtands leaning altogether to the one ſide, and what wonder, that many that ſeem wholly to lean upon it, do cry, <hi>It fulls, it falls,</hi> that was not laid upon a larger Foundation. But how did theſe Maſter-Builders proceed in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of their New-Reformed Church? It ſeemed to be built no lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than to contain one Family, the genuine Sons of ſuch Fathers; there was but one narrow Door of admiſſion to it, a ſtrong Lock upon it, and the ſole Power of the Keys was in truſty Hands, and the Sword in the hand of a Friend, there was no outward Apartment in it to entertain Strangers, or belonging to it: But ſome got a falſe Key to the Door, as many call it,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50217:22"/>a Key of <hi>a larger ſenſe;</hi> and when ſome got in, more crouded in; and ſo the <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> in Charity, came in with the <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> in Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, to the no little grief of ſome who do not like their company. The Fathers keep above Stairs, and now and then come down among us, and ſend their Officers to viſit us, and have their Watch renewed every Year to tell Tales of us, and they that are without Doors, cry, If there be any Love in our Governors to Chriſt, and his divided Flock, that we would but widen the Door, and reform but ill Cuſtoms; but we ſay, we cannot help our ſelves or them, for the Law will have it ſo. The Law had a two-edged Sword of Penalties, and ſome of them who took Sword to guard and aſſiſt the Church, having ſpent their heat, grew for the moſt part cold and lazy; and more Diſſenters were ſmitten with the Key, than the Sword: And ſo nothing almoſt went on currantly and vigorouſly, for more got into the Communion than ſome would have, and ſo many kept out, that there were too many to be dealt with. Several of the Biſhops having made work for others, and having their Wills, grew very gentle. I begin within mine own Knowledg, or good Information. I ſhall not need to ſpeak of Biſhops, <hi>Monk</hi> and <hi>Gauden,</hi> nor of <hi>Reynolds,</hi> who carried the Wounds of the Church (in his Heart and Bowels) to his Grave with him, as is well known to many that knew him: but ſpeak of the moſt rigorous at firſt hand. Doctor <hi>Laney,</hi> firſt Biſhop of <hi>Peterborough;</hi> who had made a great busſle in the croud of aſpiring Men in <hi>Cambridg,</hi> till he came up ſeveral Stories, as high as he deſired to be, was very moderate in his Government. In his prime Viſitation, (as I have heard one ſpeak that was by) before <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> he in his Chamber told ſome of his Clergy what he came about; and as tho he would wipe his Hands, ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>Not I, but the Law;</hi> and could (to uſe his own phraſe to a ſcrupulous Perſon) look through his Fingers, and ſuffer a worthy <hi>Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt</hi> to preach publickly very near him, for ſome Years together, after his remove to another Biſhoprick.</p>
               <p>Biſhop <hi>Saunderſon</hi> was ſevere, and troubled long with a ſharp Diſeaſe, which might exaſperate his Mind, had a Roll of Miniſters under his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Eye, deſigned for Diſcipline; but when he drew nigh to his latter End, he commanded that Roll to be burnt, and ſaid, He would die in Peace.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Earle</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> was a Man that could do Good againſt Evil; forgive much, and of a charitable Heart, and died, to the no great ſorrow of them, who reckoned his Death was juſt, for labouring all his might againſt the <hi>Oxford Five-mile Act.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But moſt remarkable is that Paſſage in the laſt <hi>Teſtament,</hi> printed both in <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> of the Learned Dr. <hi>Coſins</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Dureſm,</hi> printed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50217:23"/>with his Funeral Sermon and Life. He leaves a Mark upon the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, to ſatisfy us that he was none, but tells the Church, That our great and main Work is, to Unite. The Paſſage deſerves Tranſcribing, <hi>viz. pag.</hi> 126. <q>I take it to be my Duty, and of all my Brethren, eſpecially the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and Miniſters of the Church of God, to do our <hi>utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours,</hi> according to the Meaſure of Grace which is given to every one of Us, that at laſt an <hi>End</hi> may be put to the Differences of Religion, or at leaſt they may be leſſened, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>How others of their Order, that are dead, and alive, that managed that Affair, for the ſtanding or ſhaking of this Church, have carried themſelves in Debates, and great Trials, is better known to others than to me. Only I will crave leave to ſay, That one at that time but Doctor, hath not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted the quiet of peaceable conſidering Men, by provoking Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> to ſhew Reaſons of his Nonconformity, which are too hard for many to anſwer, and unanſwered yet. And it is to no purpoſe to ſet <hi>R.</hi> againſt <hi>B.</hi> and <hi>Baxter</hi> againſt <hi>Baxter,</hi> as if none could anſwer him till he turn <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt</hi> and anſwer himſelf; and it will not do, to whiſper, that the Man is rude and crack'd; for indeed, the more crack'd he is, the more Kernel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is ſeen.</p>
               <p>The wiſe and good Biſhop <hi>Wilkins,</hi> was a Man of another Spirit, and took comfort in his healing Endeavours upon his Death-bed. And the Lord of his infinite Mercy, move and engage their Right Reverend Survi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, and other eminent Divines of the Church, to lay to heart our dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, broken, and declining State, and ſupplicate the King and Parliament to unite and ſtrengthen the Proteſtant Intereſt. A far better Work, than to invite the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> to come in, as things do ſtand, or to provoke any of them to ſhew cauſe of their Nonconformity, which tends but to exaſperate ſome, and to ſhake others out of their own Communion, if they prevent it not. I do not ſpeak at all adventures. If ſome could have executed the Laws, or prevailed with Magiſtrates ſo to do, we ſhould have had a Militant Church indeed. In the Year 1669, we had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Articles ſent down to the Clergy, with private Orders to ſome, to make the Conventiclers as few and ſmall as might be;— The eighth and laſt was this, <hi>Whether you do think</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">That is, The Diſſenters.</note> 
                  <hi>they might be eaſily ſuppreſt by the Aſſiſtance of the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate?</hi> Some made bold to anſwer more than <hi>Ay,</hi> or <hi>No.</hi> Since, what encouragement had a ſort of ſcandalous Perſons to become Informers. But God took ſome of theſe into his own hand; ſome cut off, and ſome convinced; and through the gentleneſs of the Civil Magiſtrate, and ſhame of the Office, Meetings went on, and grew, as they are at this day.—Some of the Informers were ſtruck into an
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50217:23"/>Awe of the Preachers, and manner of their preaching; others baffled, and ſome, as <hi>Gibſon</hi> of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> died miſerably. <hi>See the Life of Mr.</hi> John Tregoſs.</p>
               <p>I have been large in this Head; I will be ſhorter in the reſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth Conſideration is, The Qualifications of their Perſons. They have their Faults, no doubt: The Angels of the Churches, are not Angels of Heaven. They are better known to many Great Men in Church and State, than to me, who very rarely ſee or converſe with any. But if they required my Teſtimony, I would give it, That for Loyalty to their King, I never knew any more. They cannot drink his Health, but they helpt to pray him to his Throne, pray that he may long ſit upon it, and pray him towards Heaven. They break his Laws, ſay ſome, and ſow Sedition? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Do they ſo? Then ſpare them not. They are grieved they cannot keep his Laws, that ſuch Laws are made which they cannot keep. But have they reſiſted, when their Goods have been ſeiſed, or broken Priſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What Conſpiracy have they been in? Bleſſed be God, who hath kept them above the Slanders of their Adverſaries, and convinced them (if any thing will) that they can Preach, and Pray, and not into a War; and neither Preach nor Pray us into a War, or a Plot.</p>
               <p>Their Holineſs and Morality is conſpicuous, and they are uſeful many ways in the Common-Wealth; and for their Miniſterial Abilities, allowing them but thoſe Grains which no Man of Charity denies, and no Man of any Abilities can paſs for currant without, they (are Men of different ſtatures, it is true, but ſome) are eminent for variety of excellent and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Learning, and known to the Church of God, by many rare pieces of Practical Divinity, and Controverſal. Beſide the many Tracts of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Men, that will be valued while Chriſtianity hath any Name among Ages to come. See but a Specimen of their Dexterity in Practical Divinity, in thoſe Lectures, called, <hi>The Morning Exerciſes at Cripplegate, and Supplement.</hi> For poſitive, in their Morning Exerciſes at <hi>St. Giles in the Fields,</hi> &amp;c. And their Polemical, in their Morning Exerciſes againſt Popery. and there are very able Divines and Preachers up and down the Land, beſide thoſe that are known in <hi>London.</hi> What Service hath Mr. <hi>Pool</hi>'s <hi>Nullity and Dialogues,</hi> Dr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s Anſwer to <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Key for Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Mr. <hi>Clarkson</hi>'s Moral Divinity of the Papiſts, and his Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations upon the <hi>Jeſuits Speeches,</hi> done? What a notable Book is Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi>'s <hi>Man of Sin?</hi> I hope no Man will think, that I look upon them as the only Champions in this Cauſe, or extol them, to leſſen or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive any of our Conforming Worthies of the, honour of their open and hazardous Engagements againſt that Daring Faction. No, but my Soul
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50217:24"/>longs to ſee them all under the ſame Banner, and of the ſame Body, and the ſame Denomination. The Meaſures of theſe muſt not be taken from ſome Mens Books, who had magnified their Office more, if they had not expoſed and vilified them. Are there any mean and weak among them? They may be uſeful if nouriſhed and improved; but the beſt of them all, hath no more Liberty, beſides what he ventures for, than the very meaneſt. I, would conclude, humbly propoſing theſe Queries:</p>
               <p>Firſt; <hi>Whether it is thought that any of them, are enabled from above, with Miniſterial Abilities; and inſtructed to the Kingdom of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will not deſcend ſo low as our Legal Rule of Trial;</hi> Are they fitted for the Miniſterial Office? Have they Underſtanding in the Scripture? Skill in Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal and other uſeful Learning? Are they Orthodox in Judgment, free from Hereſie? Do they conſent to the avowed Doctrines of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Have they the Gift of Utterance? Are they willing, and deſirous to ſerve in the Goſpel of Chriſt? No doubt, but from the oldeſt to the youngeſt of them, they will ſubmit to an Examination, if thought neceſſary to their Admiſſion. Beſides the full Proof that many of them have given, even to an Excellency, above moſt of our Brethren. What of all this? will be ſaid unto me, They diſſent from the Diſcipline, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Legal Worſhip. I ask again, are they for any eſſential, fundamental Parts of Apoſtolical, truly Primitive Church Government? Will they promiſe to adminiſter all the Ordinances of the Goſpel, as Chriſt enjoyned them; as the Apoſtles and their next Succeſſors did celebrate them (as nearly as can be learned from undoubted and currant Hiſtory) The chief of them ſay they can, and it is that they contend for. Laſtly, I ask; Do we think that Chriſt would have ſent them out to preach, or forbad them, the Apoſtles have given them the Right-hand of Fellowſhip, or not? Would St. <hi>Paul</hi> have rejoyced that the Goſpel was preached by them or not?</p>
               <p>Then, ſecondly, I query; <hi>Whether any that are intruſted by Jeſus Chriſt in the Over-ſight of his Church, and adminiſtration of Government and Diſcipline in it, can forbid ſuch Men to miniſter in his Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here ſeems to me, to be a Repugnancy between Chriſt and his Officers in his Church: He fits and qualifies Men with Gifts, and Furniture for his Churches Edification, and Good, who ſtand in need of them; makes them willing to ſpend and be ſpent; but the Governours of the Church will not admit them in, but caſt them out; and by their Canon judg them excommunicate: ſo whom Chriſt ſends, they refuſe. Whoſe Will ſhould ſway the Maſter of the Family, Chriſt, or his Stewards? But it will be objected, they will not conform to the Church as eſtabliſhed by Law; and better the Church ſhould looſe their Labours, than the Hedg of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50217:24"/>thrown down for them. Dr. <hi>Stilling fl. Irenic.</hi> p. 42. Says, <hi>the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate cannot forbid true Doctrine to be preached.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I humbly offer, 1. Whether any ſuch Laws ſhould be made, ſtand in force, or executed againſt Men ſound in Doctrine, and enabled by Chriſt to ſerve him? 2. Whether this Form of Government to which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conform, be that Form of Conſtitution to which they muſt ſubmit, or elſe be deprived according to the mind of Chriſt? I go upon this Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, That all particular Laws of the Church muſt agree with the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rules of Chriſt, and not be to the damage of the Church of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. 3. Whether the Apoſtolical Church-Practice, be not rather a Rule to all ſucceeding Ages to follow, than the Fourth Age which waxed wanton in Ceremonies, and caſt thoſe Ceremonious Shadows from her Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, becauſe the Sun of Imperial Favour, and Proſperity did ſhine upon her? 4. I humbly offer, that ſuppoſing that the preſent Church-Frame of Government, Diſcipline, Worſhip and Ceremonies, (which as it is with the ſcrupled Aſſents, and Additions, and Penalties, is no older than 1662.) be neareſt of any in the World, as near as may be to the Prime Primitive Apoſtolical Church; for all this, whether there be no way to be uſed, or taken with the Non-conforming Brethren (ſuppoſe them all under an Error as to this particular of Church-Government and Ceremonies) but to ſilence them, to forbid them to preach, upon ſuch penalties? Or, ought not the Governours of the Church, out of reſpect to their Maſter <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and to the Gifts and Graces which he hath given to them, and thereby commended them in his Name, to the Acceptation of his Flock, to find out ſome way to render them uſeful to the ſervice of his People; I do ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that all, whom Chriſt hath qualified with Abilities, and made wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and that have dedicated themſelves to his Service, ought to be received and imployed. (And may I ſpeak and write it trembling) Is there not implyed a Wo to them that hinder, as well as to them that preach not the Goſpel?</p>
               <p>Objection, <hi>But they are diſobedient to the Law of the Land,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, To the Temporal Laws, they ſubmit to them. To the Temporal Laws requiring Conformity, I make bold to ask, are any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by that Law to preach, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whom Chriſt hath fitted for it? then, ought not that Law to be reviſed and repealed? Are there no Conditions or Terms required by that Law, but ſuch as are ſtrictly the Terms which Chriſt (by whom the Chriſtian Magiſtrate bears Rule) hath directed them to make for all that ſhall enter into the Church? If ſo, then it muſt be a Law of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians;</hi> But there is no ſuch thing pretended. This Law was not given in the <hi>Mount.</hi> And there are many among us that are for the Expiration and Non-obligation of the fourth Law, delivered by God
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50217:25"/>himſelf. There is no temporal Law, but is nulled or amended when it appears detrimental to the Common-wealth; and why not, when the Church ſuffers by any Law, Ought not that to be looked into?</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But the Church needs them not, and there are more in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, and Countries, and Cities, that will conform, than the Revenue of the Church will maintain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is one thing to admit our Non-conforming Brethren to the Preferments of the Church, and another to the Service of the Church; admit them firſt, and God will provide for them in time: I believe they deſire not that any Man ſhould be diſplaced for them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Put them into a Capacity for the diſcharge of the Miniſterial Office, for which they are prepared, and many of them have Epiſcopal Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He that ſaith there are too many Labourers for the Work of Chriſt in the Church, muſt hold, that Chriſt gives Gifts ſuperfluous, and gives Talents to them that have no place to trade with them, or knows not the weight of the Paſtoral Charge, or the great need of Souls, and of more help.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If there be ſuch ſtore of Miniſters that there is no room, it would be acceptable to Chriſt to take care of Forreign Plantations; But alas! How many go aſtray for want of Shepheards! [<hi>See Mr.</hi> Godwin<hi>'s Negroes Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Laſtly; I doubt not, but it is in the Power of our Church Governors, to make a great Change for the great Advantage of the Church; ſome of them have a great influence upon the Legiſlation; many have intereſt in, if not, great freedom with the great Men in Power, Opportunities to ſpeak for the Mourning Church, and to ſhew them what is good; which would more become the Miniſters of Chriſt, than to expoſe the Infirmities of the <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> or miſreport their Doings. If in the preſent Exigence and Dangers of the Church, (which they are ſenſible of, becauſe of our Diviſions, or elſe many would not invite them in, or condemn them for keeping out) Our great Men in the Church do not all that in them lies to procure our Peace, they are like to anſwer for it to the Prince of Peace. They that urge the Law againſt their Brethren, muſt either convince them of the goodneſs of the Law, which they can never do, as that to which they ought, upon peril of their Salvation to ſubmit; or elſe declare their Grief, that with all their Importunities, Prayers, and favour with Men in Power, they cannot get the Law made eaſy; or elſe this lies againſt them, that many of the Church procured the Law, which was enacted upon their Advice, and to gratify them: and if ſo, then they but for a time conceal their own uncharitableneſs, under the Wing of a Law, which is pleaſing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50217:25"/>to them. It is evident to all that have Eyes to ſee, and that have two Eyes to ſee withal, who hath gotten by this Uniformity. If it be ſaid, that Popery hath got by Non-conformity, they will readily reply, Who made them <hi>Non-conformiſts?</hi> They gave them warning of the Danger, and did all that was in the power of loyal, peaceable, honeſt Men, for Unity and Peace. For my part, I cannot reply, nor confute their vindication. And ſo much for this Head.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Conſider their Behaviour ſince their unhappy Ejection, under their many Sufferings. That their Sufferings have been great, is notorious to them that know them,<note place="margin">I have ſpoken of their Sufferings once and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but not for the ſame Cauſe, nor the ſame Things.</note> or have Chriſtian Bowels in them. To what end ſhall I make a diſtribution of them, into Spirituals, into Temporals, into Perſonal, and Domeſtical? They are condemned for making a Separation; of all Men in the Land they have the greateſt cauſe to be for Union, and againſt Separation. They have ſuffered many cutting Separations! ſuch as, from the Magiſtrates Favour and good Opinion; from their beloved Congregations; from their Habitations and Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; from their Libraries and Studies; from their own Friends, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the worldly-wiſe; from their former Familiars; from their Wives and Children. Abundance of them have been made of the Order of Mendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants, to eat other Mens Bread, to wear other Mens Cloaths, to procure their own Liberty, and to diſpoſe of their Children to Callings with other Mens Mony and Charity. Theſe things are nothing indeed to them that have no Sences! Have they ſuffered in their Names, in their Liberties, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, where they got their Deaths, as above-ſaid? It hath been a dear Separation to them! The Nonconformity hath loſt ſome Miniſters many thouſand pounds. And what have all theſe things been for? For their own Faults, Humours, factious Nature? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Have none of them any Wit, Reaſon, Policy, Religion, Conſcience? Are all ſo naught, or ſo fooliſh, ſuch Babes or Mad-men, that they hate Peace, hate their Wives and Children, and their own Fleſh? Or, cannot chuſe what's beſt, a good Living, or a naſty Priſon, or be in peril of it? O that we would forbear to judg our Fellow-Servants! They declare plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and truly,<note place="margin">They that think them to be againſt a Church-Government, becauſe they cannot conform to all particulars in this, are much miſtaken.</note> they cannot conform to the preſent Conſtitution; Who ſhould beſt know that, They, or We? Will it follow we can, therefore they may? Or, that good Men have, therefore all good Men can? Two things have been declared by them.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:50217:26"/>
                  <item>1. That they cannot forbear then Miniſtry; preach they muſt.</item>
                  <item>2. As dear as Preaching is to them, and the Magiſtrates favour, and a portion of the ſetled Maintenance, yet they cannot comply on the Legal Terms.</item>
               </list>
               <p>But have they attempted their Liberty by any treacherous Conſpiracies? Have they preached Seditiouſly? or been <hi>Achans</hi> in the Camp, or <hi>Nadabs</hi> and <hi>Abihu's?</hi> They ask no Favour, fear no Accuſations. They may ſay, as that excellent Mr. <hi>Joſeph Allen,</hi> in his gallant Speech (wiſe, humble, and fully to the Judg, when ſentenced to pay <hi>a hundred Mark,</hi> and lie in Priſon till it was paid; <q>He was glad that it had appeared, before his Country, that whatſoever he was charged with, he was guilty of nothing but doing his Duty; and that all that did appear by the Evidence, was only, That he had ſung a <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and inſtructed his Family, others being there, and both in his own Houſe; and that if nothing which had been urged, would ſatisfy, he ſhould, with all chearfulneſs and thankfulneſs, accept whatſoever Sentence his Lordſhip ſhould pronounce upon him, for ſo good and righteous a Cauſe.</q> [<hi>Life of Mr.</hi> Jof. Allen, <hi>pag.</hi> 59.]</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>But ſome of them gather Churches, Preach in time of Publick Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and are ill-tempered Men,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I meddle not in this, as it is a Matter of Controverſy, ſtated and agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated by different Perſuaſions: But as it is a Matter of Complaint; and ſo, I ſay, we ought to do all that good Men can do, for one Mind, one Way, to narrow Controverſies, by enlarging Conditions of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Many cannot help preaching in time of publick Service.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Becauſe elſe they cannot preach at all, for the diſtance of their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors.</item>
                  <item>2. Againſt their Wills they are conſtrained, becauſe many that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to hear the Publick Miniſters, would be drawn to Meetings of <hi>Anabaptiſts:</hi> And this was one reaſon which good Dr. <hi>Staunton</hi> in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, gave for his preaching at St. <hi>Albans</hi> at ſuch times. So; many of the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> are a ſecond Sieve; if they preach not, much Corn would fall to the gathered heaps of other Diſſenters.</item>
                  <item>3. Seeing they are under an Obligation of Preaching, in one ſence, the more publick their preaching is, the better, for then they will be ſure to preach nothing but what all may hear.</item>
                  <item>4. The Law makes no difference between Publick and their own Houſes, if they exceed Five; if therefore they Judg themſelves (and none can better judg than themſelves) obliged to preach upon peril of the Law, they take the more publick Places, no greater Penalties being to be ſuffered for that, than a meer private Corner.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:50217:26"/>
Laſtly, Hath any of them ſuffered as an evil Doer? (taking evil doing in the common ſence) or deſarved to ſuffer theſe eighteen Years? Have they not aſſerted the Common Intereſt? ſought the publick Welfare? op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Popery? and been as obedient Subjects to the King as any other, ſave only in this controverted Point? What pity is that, the Boſom of the Church were not as open and as large as the King's gracious Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is to them, as leading peaceable and quiet Lives, in all Godlineſs and Honeſty!</p>
               <p>What tho they complained! have they ſeaſe, or are they ſtupid! Have they ſtirred Sedition, and diſtracted the Government? taking the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a horrid Plot to play their own Game; or laid a Counter-mine, (as it pleaſed one of our Moderators, or Plot-diſcoverers to entitle his Book)—If they are ſo gracious with the rich Tradeſmen, and populace, it ſhall be to their Honour, and is to their Comfort, that they have made no other uſe of the goodneſs of the People, than to ſave their Souls. How glad ſhould all true Proteſtants he, that the Presbyterian Plot, is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len together with their own Popiſh Plot, upon the ſame Pates! Or was the Separation of the <hi>Non-conformits</hi> the Door by which Popery was entering in? Then indeed the Door muſt be ſtopt up by all means. But by this time, it is but too apparent, and with grief be it written, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> had bred ſuch Birds, as would have plucked out her Eyes. The Heifers always went in the Church-yard, with which the Papiſts plow'd; ſhameleſs Hypocrites that cried up the Church, to throw it down!</p>
               <p>Not to multiply Objections and Anſwers. It is, or may be clear, that nothing but Conſcience of Sin and Duty doth govern the Learned, Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and honeſt <hi>Non-conformiſts.</hi> I ſuppoſe there are many of them that deſerve theſe Characters: and becauſe they are governed by their Judgments and Conſciences; it is the great Duty of Governors to have reſpect to them, and to take away all Occaſions of our Bleeding Diviſions. It is in the Power of our Governors, to remove the Cauſes, and not in them. If the Judgment and Conſciences of our Governours, be to walk ſtrictly, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rule and Meaſure of our Conformity, and cannot relax, nor remove any part of it; and the Judgment of the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> be, that they cannot come up to it: then the Diviſions muſt remain as now they are, and the Deciſion be deferred to the laſt coming of Jeſus Chriſt. But may it not be decided before that? for where hath Chriſt made the Governors Conſciences the exact Meaſure of other Miniſters? But our Laws declare moſt of the things in Controverſy, to be in their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture indifferent, to be mutable, and therefore it is in their Power to take away both the Things, and the Obligation to them; and to bind us only
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50217:27"/>to the Obſervation of neceſſary things, and to leave things which they found indifferent, as they found them, without judging one another. And for this reaſon, Wiſdom and Charity requires a relaxation upon their parts; and they have this to plead for them, that they have long tried to bring Miniſters and People to an uniformity in theſe things, but could not; and therefore, for Peace, and Love, Unity, and Edification, they have taken away their Obligation.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> cannot ſubſcribe, and declare, and ſubject themſelves to this Yoke (how eaſy ſoever it ſeems to many) becauſe they cannot in their Judgment and Conſcience approve and do them, needs no great labour to prove it, to any Man of Charity.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Becauſe their Intereſt, as well as Duty, hath put them upon the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtudy of the Caſe. And being Men of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Light,<note place="margin">Beſide Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Corbet,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; The Sacried Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erarchy, and the ſmall Treatiſe of Scandal, and indifferent Things, give evidence of cloſe and deep inveſtigation of things.</note> Labour, and of Years, they may be ſuppoſed as fit to find out their own part, as other Men to find it for them. And to any that hath but the deſire to ſee, patience to read, and that thinks not to throw them off with a ſcornful Huff; they have written like Men of Parts, Judgment, and Temper. And they daily almoſt ſend abroad into the World, the Iſſues of ſerious Thoughts, and ripe Underſtandings, and Appearances of great Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs and Reſolution.</item>
                  <item>2. They do not follow the Dictates of a weak and erring Conſcience, but fear to ſin againſt a tender Conſcience, upon the beſt information of their Judgments. There is a great difference between a weak Conſcience, and a tender Conſcience; a weak Conſcience follows a weak Judgment, and the clearer and ſtronger the Judgment is, the more tender ſhould tho Conſcience be. It may therefore ſeem, that their diſſent proceeds not from their Weakneſs, and that their obſtinacy proceeds not from their Will, as oppoſing Light and Reaſon; but from the ſettlement and determination of their Judgment and their Sincerity, not daring to act againſt their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But if it were their Weakneſs, it muſt be indulged; if it were their Obſtinacy againſt Reaſon, (which appears not) what will a wiſe Father do with a ſtomachful Child? Will he provoke and encreaſe his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, by requiring of him needleſs things with great rigour, and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther qualify and win him?</item>
                  <item>3. If it be not Conſcience of Sin that makes them diſſent, it is either their Policy for ſome worldly Intereſt, or their Folly. If the firſt, then it cannot conſiſt with worldly Policy, to take ways directly contrary to what they aim at. What honour is it for a Man to be railed upon, reviled,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50217:27"/>ſuſpectd? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What Profit is it for a Man to quit a Certainty for an Uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty? and to live precariouſly? Where the Policy of <hi>Non-Conformity</hi> lies, doth not appear to me. Is it their Folly? Are there no wiſe Men among them? not one! They have had Experience by this time to make them wiſe, if nothing elſe. If they are Fools, it is for <hi>Chriſt.</hi> They come not behind their Neighbours for Wit, and Abilities.</item>
                  <item>4. What, but Conſcience of Sin and Duty, could afford them that Peace and Joy, in Diſgraces and Sufferings, in Hazards both living and dying! You'l ſay, <hi>Fanaticiſm</hi> may end in fancied Joys and Comforts. True, but theſe Men could as well diſtinguiſh between the Effects of Imagination, and Self-examination, between a Rock and Sand, and have taken as much pains to avoid a Cheat, as other Men. It muſt be granted, that many that have drawn Sufferings upon themſelves deſervedly, by their Imprudence, have flattered themſelves in high Conceits, and conceited Comforts. But whether the Sufferings of Men of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ripeneſs of Judgment, Inquiſitiveneſs into their Caſe, their Reaſons, Motives, and after Prayer and Diligence, have deliberately choſen a ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Part, and found Comfort from the Conſcience of their Sincerity, be no more than the Comfort of a Hypocrite under the Power of Deluſion, ought not raſhly to be cenſured, and be rejected, as no Argument of their being conſcientious?</item>
                  <item>5. If they are not conſcientious in their <hi>Non-conformity,</hi> then they are diſobedient to the King, and the Laws; they are Factious, Diſturbers of the Churches Peace, Schiſmatical, and Enemies to the Churches Growth and Union; they are hypocritical, and in a word Atheiſtical; they are unrighteous, unkind, unmerciful to their own Fleſh, to their Wives and Children, oppreſſive to thoſe few that are liberal to them; yea many have deſtroyed themſeves, and no leſs than this can be ſaid of their Way, that it is the high-way of Sin and certain Damnation. And if they are ſuch wicked Perſons, ſuch Hypocrites in Masks and Cloaks, they are but uſed too well; and better they ſhould be out of the Church, than in it. But then to bring them off from theſe horrid Imputations; theſe things are conſiderable,</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. If they were not Men of Integrity and Conſciences, they would not keep without, becauſe there is more to be got within. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they are not the only conſcientious Men; for there are many thouſands I hope, of ſincere, good Men that conform, that have Peace and Comfort in a faithful diſcharge of their Duties. But, I ſay, if our Diſſenting Brethren were not conſcientious, and ſincere, then they would ſwallow Oaths or Declarations, ſubſcribe to Salt and Spittle, for the ſake of the preſent World. He that acts not with reſpect to the World,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50217:28"/>to come, muſt needs act for the good things of this. Now 'tis clear, that the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> have the higher Honour, and Precedence, and the fatteſt Morſels.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Our <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> have a better Character, and are looked upon as Conſcientious Men, and fit for the Churches Service; 1. Becauſe of the due Reſpect, and Repute they have among Men of Parts, Eſtates and Temper. 2. Becauſe of the many Invitations, and even Chidings to unite and come in: which ſuppoſeth them to be Men of Worth and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or elſe the further off the better. 3. Becauſe of the oft vaniſhing talk of an Indulgence in the firſt Years of their <hi>Non-Conformity, Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion,</hi> ſince, and <hi>fair Promiſes</hi> often made. 4. Becauſe that many Juſtices of the Peace angry enough for the Church, and not pleaſed with them, have forborn to act againſt them, and could not find in their Hearts to execute the Laws upon Conſcientious Men, though of different Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions. My Concluſion is, That they appear to be Men of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and if ſo, way ſhould be made for their coming in. One thing is urged to prejudg their tenderneſs, that Conſcientious Men ſhould come as far they can, and as near a cloſure as may be. Ah! what though they can do much, yet as to actual Admiſſion, It is not doing ſome or many things that will bring them in; for they muſt declare and ſubſcribe to all and every thing. I knew a Man of Years and Parts, that could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to all things, ſave the Croſs, and loſt near 200 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr> per Annum,</hi> for that. It is all or nothing in this caſe. If we would bring them in, take down the narrow Doors, and make them a Paſſage of juſt Dimenſion and Latitude upon theſe Premiſes, That the Caſe of the Diſſenting Brethren is hard; that what they demanded, or propoſed, upon the Kings Commiſſion, to the Biſhops and the Commiſſioners for the Church, were but what was thought fit to be conſidered of by Men, no doubt of as great Learning, and other Qualifications, as any other of the ſame Quality; That their Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings have been very great, their Demeanour peaceable, their Abilities valuable, and their Diſſent conſcientious. I do humbly conclude, and propoſe it to my Reverend Superiours, in any place of Power, Favour or Intereſt, that they would ſincerely endeavour the qualifying of theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Perſons, for a legal diſcharge of their Miniſterial Duties: A thing ſo pleaſing to God, agreeable to the Government and Condeſcention of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to the Chriſtian Temper; ſo conducing to the Churches Union, Peace, Growth and eſtabliſhment; to the ſilencing of many Controverſies, and that fearful Clamour and Accuſation of Schiſm, that I am not able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it. I cannot, it is acknowledged, judg what is another Man's par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Duty; but I humbly conceive it is mine in my place (which is but low indeed) to provoke any Superiours to it. And if I were in their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50217:28"/>place (which is but a Suppoſition next to a Dream) I ſhould neither eat, nor drink, not ſleep with Satisfaction, till this were done, or endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured; nor think of appearing before <hi>Jeſus</hi> the Chief Shepherd, with Joy or Acceptation. Hath he required this Uniformity at our hands, of this Extent, with theſe Sanctions, having for many Years ſeen no better Effects of them?</p>
               <p>Hath not his Gracious Majeſty by a late Proclamation for a great, and neceſſary Duty of faſting and Prayers, made this one end of that Solemn Duty, to unite the Hearts of his Proteſtant Subjects? Have we not in one Prayer repreſentd bleeding Wounds from our Diviſions, and in another prayed for Union? Have many taken Direction to wreſtle with God, (Laugh and Scorn who dare at the Word) to grant us that Bleſſing? And what was the meaning of it? Was no more to be underſtood by it, than to bring the Diſſenting Brethren on a ſudden to ſee, what after many Years Study, Prayers and Sufferings they cannot ſee? On a ſudden to convert them againſt their Reaſon? And to condemn themſelves for their Diſſent. Surely, I cannot think it: for what were this but to pray for an Impoſſibility or a Miracle, and to pray in vain, in our Solemn Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! If Union be ſo deſirable a Mercy, as certainly it is; what ſhall we do for Union? Are there no other Terms of Union but theſe? Without doubt it is their great Sin, not to come as near to a Cloſure as poſſibly they can; but doth all the Duty lye on their ſide; and no more upon us, than to call them in? And if not, let them be excommunicated from the Church, if not accurſed of God! Or were they never meant? As be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Proteſtants; or not Loyal Subjects? And what are they that ſay or think ſo? The Lord in Mercy grant, he may not ſee ſuch a Trial, as I doubt not they would by the Grace of God, as forwardly engag'd in, as true Proteſtants, and as Loyal Subjects to the King and Government, to the Expence and Profuſion of their deareſt Blood.</p>
               <p>I cannot think any thing more ſuitable to the Clemency of the King's Nature, who hath always been ready to gratify peaceble Deſigns. Can we think it is not ſuitable to the Conſtitution of the late Great, and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Parliament, or to any other that ſhall be choſen by a free Election? This great Body hath as quick diſcerning Eyes as ever any other had, and have made as deep Diſcoveries of the Works of Darkneſs as any other, for their time: and ſee a neceſſity of uniting Proteſtants at home, and ſuccouring Proteſtants abroad; and cannot they diſcern, by what Perſons, whoſe Endeavours, to whoſe purpoſes our Conſtitutions have been ſcrewed ſo high? They are not unſenſible by whom they have been called a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Paliament, and who are afraid of their undoing all: Perhaps in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they would think it hard Meaſure, that every Man in <hi>England</hi> ſhould
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50217:29"/>be turned out of Doors, that will not be content that his Houſe ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly Uniform. They may by Experience know that there may be Peace and Unity, and Charity in Houſes, that are of different Figure and Form. There is a vaſt Difference between pulling down painted Glaſs, which keeps out Light, and making Doors wider, or taking down ſome Partiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and pulling down of Houſes. Oh! let it never be ſaid, that Church-Men are moſt moroſe, difficult, and ſtiff, and can grant nothing, but in a great Extremity.</p>
               <p>And I pray God that he would move, and effectually work upon their Hearts, to take the Opportunities and Advantages God puts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Hands, to ſupplicate and promote the great Work of Healing. It will be a Work moſt pleaſing to all <hi>Conformiſts,</hi> that have the trueſt Principles of Chriſtianity, that are not factious to keep what they have, or think the gain of Peace to the Church, will bring a loſs to of them; or that are not Melancholy, and given to pore upon Shadows, and to think their Fancies to be the unalterable Frame of Antiquity. If we cannot diſtinguiſh between an Alteration and a Diſſolution; between Reformation (of what hath been changed one way or other, in every Princes Reign, ſince the 2d of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.) and an Extirpation, we are not Cathedral-men, that know the Note may be changed, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument unbroken, and that the ſame <hi>Pſalm</hi> may be read and ſung.</p>
               <p>Many cry out upon <hi>Schiſm,</hi> that miſs of the Notion; It is a very great Sin! Should we not therefore do what poſſibly we can, to remove the Cauſes, and to redeem Souls from the Sin and Guilt of it? To this end, let us take notice, that the Carnal Heart is the Seat of <hi>Schiſm.</hi> Are there no Schiſmatical Notions, or Paſſions and Luſts in us within the Pale? We know that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in Diſcipline and Modes of Worſhip, could not extinguiſh, or reſtrain Diviſions in former days. How was the Church divided between thoſe two, the prevailing and riſing <hi>Arminian</hi> Innovators, and the <hi>Anti-Arminian</hi> Propugnators of the Doctrine and ancient Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church? And the Feuds were greater between theſe in many Reſpects, than between the <hi>Conformiſt</hi> and <hi>Non-Conformiſt.</hi> And the ſtraining of the Girdle of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> burſt the Buckles, and the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hung looſe, till by a new Act, the Girdle was made ſtronger, and leſs than it was before, and new Buckles made a purpoſe for it. —</p>
               <p>There is an Unity, where there is not an Uniformity, and <hi>Vice verſa.</hi> To what Church in <hi>London</hi> can a Man go, and find an Uniformity, exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly keeping with Rubricks and Orders? and yet there is a <hi>Conformity,</hi> and in general an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> I might inſtance in Miniſters, and People's deviating from the Rule, in Prayers. What Uniformity among the People? ſome ſtanding, others kneeling, and others leaning, if not ſitting; Some facing the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:50217:29"/>
                  <hi>Eaſt,</hi> others the <hi>Weſt,</hi> and others the <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South;</hi> ſome uſe the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponds, ſome low, and others loud, and others ſilent; and yet there may be an Unity in the <hi>Amen,</hi> either oral or mental. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> will never be forced to Particulars, it muſt lie in Generals, as Unity in Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials. God both in the works of Nature, Providence and Grace, is moſt glorious in Variety, in Multiformity. Uniformity as it is an outward ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of Unity, and as a help to Unity and Edification, and Peace, is moſt deſirable; but too rigorous preſſing of it, is one cauſe of <hi>Schiſms;</hi> and <hi>Contentions.</hi> To a clear ſtating of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> we muſt enquire into the Church as inviſible, viſible, as in its one Eſſential Nature, ſeparate from Legal Eſtabliſhment, and in its Legal Eſtabliſhment; and accordingly diſtinguiſh of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> which is aggravated from Circumſtances. In our days <hi>Non-Conformity</hi> and <hi>Schiſm</hi> are made convertible, whereas the internal Cauſes may be in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts,</hi> as well as <hi>Non-Conformiſts.</hi> But what is the external Bond and Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Conformity?</hi> what makes the <hi>Conformiſt,</hi> and what makes the <hi>Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt?</hi> Take away the Mount and Pale, and the Incloſure and the Open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field is all one Field for the Flocks to feed together. Some have extolled the Act of Uniformity as a bleſſed Act; and ſome as the Bulwark of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion. It muſt be acknowledged that it is a Bleſſing to the Church, to have nurſing Fathers, and to have our Religion eſtabliſhed by Law. But he that is the Author and Founder of our Religion is the Bulwark alſo, and the King's Life and Conſtancy is a wonderful Mercy to us: But alas! what a Fence is the Act, if the Governours were changed? The Proteſtant Religion as Chriſtian, as oppoſite to Popery, was before the Act was; and would be, if it were reviſed and changed. The moſt that can be made of the Separations, is, that they are illegal, and the aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Schiſm</hi> illegal. The Differences are originally in the minds of Men, and forced out by an Act. From this the <hi>Conformiſt</hi> and <hi>Non-Conformiſt</hi> receive their Denominations. Before this, were Dr. <hi>Bates,</hi> Dr. <hi>Jacomb,</hi> Dr. <hi>Anneſly,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gouge,</hi> and others, <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> any more than the learned Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Neſt?</hi> They could edify the Church together, carry on the Morning Exerciſe together, and converſe as Brethren. But ſince a new Door and Partition hath been ſet up, they appear to be as two Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and two Parties (I doubt not but the Dean's Catholick Head and Heart can take them in.) If they hear him not, perhaps they may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur the angry Mark of Separation; if he hear any of them, he may incur a Disfavour. Take away the Doors, and Partition-walls, and the Houſe is one again. And there are great ſuſpicions that the Surveyors made the Doors for Excluſion, and not a large Admiſſion.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. If you conſider; that which was an offenſive Innovation to a <hi>Brown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig, Ward, Prideaux,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(quanti viri!)</hi> is now made Legal, <hi>viz.</hi> the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50217:30"/>ſervice in <hi>Latin</hi> in the Univerſities, <hi>Weſtminſter, Wincheſter, Eaton,</hi> when they pleaſe, as was noted before.</item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> of old ſtuck at Subſcriptions, <hi>ex animo,</hi> to the Canon; but by this they muſt ſubſcribe and declare, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a ſure way to win them!</item>
                  <item>3. Not only to Articles of Religion (which was enough for a <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt.</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s days) but all and every thing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. Did ſome think that Biſhops and Presbyters were but one Order? Now to keep them out, the Biſhop is conſecrated in a new Form, to the Office of a Biſhop, as a Superiour Order; at leaſt as ſome conceive.</item>
                  <item>5. Many had taken the Covenant, which renounced not the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, and by virtue of theſe conjunctly, did adhere to Kingly Government, under the Uſurpation, and endeavoured to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the King. But now that muſt be renounced (ſtill to help to bring in more) into Conformity, was it not the way? Will they for Peace and Union quit the Directory, and conform to a Liturgy? it ſhall not bring them in! Would they have the Liturgy amended? They ſhall not, but in as few things as may be. Can they uſe the Ceremonies rather than be deprived? they muſt declare openly as much. Can they practiſe the old Conformity? They ſhall renounce the Covenant, by which they were bound to endeavour a Reformation? Would they become Lecturers, as heretofore they might be? No, not except they declare Aſſent and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent once a month. If one thing will not keep them out, another ſhall; if nothing at all will keep them out, then they are hardly truſted without great Evidences, if not Recantations. And who are moſt gratified and encouraged to come in, but a Man whoſe Conſcience can reach many Miles to two ſeveral Dioceſſes, it may be, from Living to Living? He hath no more to do, but to come within his time, and declare according to Law, and read his Certificate of renouncing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Law hath nothing more to require of him, ſave that where he is Reſident, or Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, and hath no Impediment; then indeed he ſhall read the Service, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> once a Month, or forfeit five Pound. If a Man loves his Eaſe or his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, let him conform; all the difficulty is in getting in: If he will, he may do any thing <hi>per alium,</hi> except dye, and give up his Accounts.—When I conſider theſe things, I do not wonder there are ſo many <hi>Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts.</hi>—</item>
               </list>
               <p>That Honour of his Profeſſion, and our Age, and either the Example, or the Shame of them that ſhall ſucceed, Sr. <hi>Matthew Hales,</hi> ſaid (to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> on whoſe word I take it) this Act of Uniformity will never unite and heal us; and did upon occaſion draw up a new Bill of Uniformity. His Judgment might as ſoon be taken as any Mans; and becauſe his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50217:30"/>and Manuſcripts, are in honour with our late, wiſe, and great Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I pray God that Bill may not be over-look'd, when that Honourable Aſſembly ſhall meet again to debate it.</p>
               <p>Here I could ſtop without the decency of concluſion, my running thoughts being put to a ſtand, and ready to yeeld to a prevailing Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, and grief of Heart.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe ſo few Heads and Hands were united, and at work, to repair the Breaches of a great Church, which ſhould be every good Man's Prayer and Endeavour.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Becauſe the Reſult of the Debates, and Counſels of tho but few, yet great, wiſe, and good Men, ſhould be rejected.</p>
               <p>But why ſhould we look for better from thoſe Men, who ſaw not what they had done amiſs, nor repented of other great Evils, which the whole Nation hath ſeen and felt, when Men's Principles are but as Wheels, moved by Intereſt, the Intereſt muſt be changed, before the Wheels turned backward? Souldiers of Fortune prolong a War, and Counſellors of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune prolong Diſtractions. The Troubles of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that put the Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men into a diſorder, and ſcotch'd the Wheels of many of our Chariots, were never for the drawing of them into one Body again, and making them ſerviceable. Some grave and good Men checked the progreſs of the reſt, and at laſt the beſt over-awed the Guilty, and did gallantly bear up againſt daring <hi>Rome:</hi> But the Oppoſition had been the more ſucceſsful and ſecure, if they had brought the differing Parties of Proteſtants into a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Truſt and Aſſurance. Bleſſed be the Men, and bleſſed be their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, and bleſſed be their Counſels, who have laboured to heal the hurt of the Daughter of <hi>Sion!</hi> and happy they who firſt arrive at the Haven, tho upon the Planks of a torn and broken Church! The Men of a <hi>Moſaic</hi> Spirit, would have ſet the contending <hi>Iſraelites</hi> at one; but our wiſe Men would not believe a Bill of Union. They who had done the wrong, thruſt the Reconcilers away, <hi>q. d.</hi> Who made you Judges? But our Time was not, and is not yet come, altho we have had a great Body, inſpired with as great a Soul as ever breathed within thoſe Walls, that ſaw a like neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of including Proteſtants, as of excluding Papiſts. Theſe ſee the Things of our Peace, but cannot overtake Peace. <hi>Perfidious Proteſtants</hi> (ſo called in the Humble Addreſs, <hi>Nov.</hi> 29. 1680.) could not find the way of Peace in his Majeſty's Reſtauration, it was as far above them, as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is above the Earth, nor knew how to imploy the Sword &amp; Treaſure but againſt Proteſtants abroad; nor then Power, but upon Proteſtants at home,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50217:31"/>who helped to reſtore them to it;<note place="margin">They may read their Character in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Proclamation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Debaucheries, <hi>1660.</hi> printed, and to be read in Churches.</note> nor their Peace, but in Effeminacy, Debaucheries, contempt of God, and the Power of that Religion, which they either contracted into an uneaſy corner of a Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or elſe enlarged as far as <hi>Rome.</hi> They who reared too high a Wall about the Church, have not ſeen the influence of the Sun upon it, to impregnate it into a deſired fruitfulneſs; the few Plants of a purer kind that ſpring up in it, look pale and yellow, faint and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guid: There is a great noiſe and ſound of Religion, but little Life and Soul! What a brood of Atheiſts, Papiſts, Zealous Formaliſts and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders have grown up? Since a Bill of Divorce was iſſued out to ſeparate able Miniſters from their Congregations, an illegitimate Race ſprung up, who cry up, Law, Law, and ſin againſt the Confeſſions and Prayers im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon us by it: And the Church, which was the moſt pregnant Mother of ſolid and holy Chriſtians of any in the World, after many Years traveland pains, ſees more of the ſhape and form, than of the lively Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and ſtrength of true Piety. They who take themſelves to be wronged, and the Divorce to be null in it ſelf, have come together, (tho but now and then, and by ſtealth, for moſt part, till of late) are liable to the Courts for unlawful Society with their eſpouſed People, have rather multiplied Sorrows, than multiplied Joys. Reſtore the Prophets their Wives; or if they are dead by Law, give them Licenſes to marry where they can; mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the unmarried, and they will, as they do, pray for you; and the Church that is now weak, and ſickly, ſhall be the joyful Mother of Children, born and brought up for God. Take in more Labourers, there is Field<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>room enough, and the Harveſt will be the greater, and ſo the Joy in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p>To draw to a Concluſion; I will firſt point out the Obſtructors of our Union.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Give my Opinion, that the Caſe of the <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> that are found in Faith, peaceable, and godly, is that which no Man need be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of, or to appear in as an Interceſſor.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Indeed I am troubled, that there are any ſuch to be found in a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church, and of all other, in this Church, that oppoſe or hinder a Coaleſeence. But all are not <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that are of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Many of the Church are for it, and againſt it: are for it, in its preſent ſtate of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement, and not for it in an Enlargement, which will be really for its Glory and juſt Authority. What Multitudes are there of theſe, both High
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50217:31"/>and Low? I will pray for them that are above me, and ſpeak of them that are near upon a level with me. I might divide theſe into Clergy and Laity; I will keep me to the firſt, becauſe they do influence many of the other. But by the way, I will take up a Remark: It is ſo come to paſs, that our driving and compelling Clergy, have fewer Admirers and Friends than they once had. Many Men, of little or no Religion in Judgment and Heart, could not bear the plain and preſſing Preaching of many able Miniſters, reputed to be unlearned; becauſe conſtant and popular Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, they could eaſily part with theſe, and give reſt to their own Eats, by ſtriking them dumb. They were tickled, if not captivated, by the flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid and gentile Preaching, and Writings of ſome (of a more Romantick, than true Majeſtick and Divine Stile) of the Sons of the Church, and therefore ſay, Let theſe preach, and the reſt keep ſilence. Some of theſe kept up the Repute of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> under its Oppreſſion, that loſt it in its Exaltation. When their Feathers were grown, and covered with yellow Gold, they ſpared their Voices, fled from Preferment to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, to gather Gold, but ſpread not their Wings to ſucker and cheriſh their Brood.</p>
               <p>Theſe were the Maſters of the Religion of the Courtiers; and many being tired with the Uſurpation, gave up their own Reaſon in comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Courtiers, for a time, did eaſily ſubmit to what was determined by our Leaders. And who were they? Church-Papiſts, as well as Church-Proteſtants; ſome of whom were carried beyond their own temper of Moderation; firſt, to ſtrain hard to practice, what really they adjudged of an evil Tendency, tho of an indifferent Nature, as they thought; and then they were to exact of others, what they could do themſelves. The more diſcerning and obſtinate, ſaw the Journeys end of theſe Charioteers; and were reſolved on their own way: Others that were peaceable and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile, complied, in hopes of the eſtabliſhment of the King's Declaration; and were held in Parlee, till their Enemies ('tis a ſad, but too true a word) got that Power, as to force them to yeeld or fly. The Gentleman, underſtanding the Myſtery of the Church-Government was Power, and the Myſtery of many Church-mens Zeal, was Church-Dignities, ſaw that he muſt Act and Vote, not for the pure Intereſt of Religion, but the temporal Intereſt of theſe Deſigning Men, began to recoil, and then to look to his own Ground. Many of theſe rode in Company, but ſeeing the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were reſolved for <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Rome;</hi> when they had gone as far as <hi>Ganterbury</hi> and <hi>Dover,</hi> and kept pace with them, were reſolved to go no further, but to turn back, and break from the Company. The reſt of the Church-Conformiſts, were either the ſame, or like them that were in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50217:32"/>and continued the ſame painful courſe in their Miniſtry, or took cold, became idle, hot, intemperate, and offenſive: The firſt have ſome reſpect, the others, no more than they deſerve. A new Generation come up with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe eighteen or twenty Years; many of them take the riſing Side, Cant ſome Scraps that fall from their Leaders Mouths; preach as much with their Teeth as with their Tongues; being neither ſtudious, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate, nor modeſt, but venturers in Cenſures; they are thought unfit to direct and overſee the Souls of Men. Upon ſome ſolemn Times, upon ſome ſolemn Days, they Diſcharge freely, but Aim with an evil Eye, ſcare away ſome Birds, but convince no Man of Sin, or Duty. The Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of all Degrees, ſpare not to declare their diſlike of theſe Men. In a word, The growth of Popery, and the antipathy that is kindled againſt it, by the fiery Deſigns of Papiſts, and the Light of Truth; the Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome eminent diſcerning Church-men, the good Behaviour of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, the weakneſs of the Proteſtant Intereſt, by our needleſs Diviſions, the ſobriety of our Gentry, the unanimity both of them; and the able Country-men, and Citizens, and their Zeal, ſeeing all at Stake, doth ſeem to open a way to a deſired Union, notwithſtanding the averſation of ſuch Oppoſers as I ſhall name.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A Party of Rigid Impoſers, Impoſers in Opinion, not yet in Power, that's the beſt of it; they mightily take the Yoke, Saddle, and Collar of Bells, and the Rack in which we muſt follow, as the only way. We being Subjects, muſt not judg, but ſubmit; and they being Judges, weigh to every Man the ſame weight; the Weakeſt muſt bow down to as great a Load as the ſtrongeſt, whether they can bear it or not; and meaſure to every Man his <hi>Omer,</hi> whether he can digeſt it, or not, (if it were all <hi>Manna,</hi> directly from Heaven, a weak Perſon muſt ſtrive to ſwallow it) but yet God, that allowed an <hi>Omer</hi> to every one that could, did not require it of every one that could not, upon pain of turning out, and not coming within five miles of the Family. If <hi>Saul</hi> had been of theſe Mens Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>David</hi> muſt not kill <hi>Goliah</hi> like a <hi>Non-conformiſt,</hi> but go forth with his Armour, his Helmet, and Coat of Male, and gird on his Sword; but he was ſo reaſonable, that ſeeing <hi>David</hi> could not go with them, he ſhould go without the Formalities of a Champion. There may be as great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportions between the underſtandings of ſome young unſtudied Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, and the underſtandings of great Doctors, as was between <hi>David</hi>'s Head, and <hi>Saul</hi>'s Head and Helmet; the things required for <hi>Aſſent,</hi> are much too big for their Capacities: But every <hi>I. A. B.</hi> that is but <hi>B. A.</hi> or a Deacon, muſt <hi>Aſſent and Conſent, Declare, Abbor,</hi> as perfectly as any <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of Divinity,</hi> as poſitively as if he were an <hi>Arch Biſhop.</hi> They muſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50217:32"/>ſee theſe things with other Mens Eyes, or muſt not take the Work upon them, and yet have not the help of a Licenſed Comment, upon (as ſome think) a hard Leſſon. I ſhould think, Catechiſe the Noviſes well in our Articles, and when they Aſſent, let them Aſſent to what they underſtand, and no more; and if <hi>Conſent to the uſe</hi> be the meaning of the thing, tell them plainly ſo. I am for a plain and eaſy way, and as light a Burden as may be laid, that ſo we may have the more and better Company, and the more comfortable Journey. (Pardon the haſtineſs of my Pen, in ſaying, what I am for; Who am I? and the Buſineſs is not come to my Voting.)—But theſe large and intricate Impoſitions, being equal upon all, Unlearned as well as Learned, do preſerve a Notion ſomewhat like an Implicit Faith: and not <hi>toto Coelo,</hi> different from an Infallibility. — But, ſay they, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to eradicate bad Principles out of the minds of Men which grew up in the late Times. I demand whether out of the minds of them that are planted with them? (But can my Declaration convert another, and root out ill Principles out of his mind? What if he doth not ſee the reaſon of my Opinion?) or out of the minds that never received thoſe pernicious Principles? Yet ſtill I only declare for my ſelf, and if I was never infected with them, there is no danger of my <hi>propagating of them;</hi> let us propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Godlineſs and Honeſty, and theſe Principles will never grow up by them. The Principles had been buried in the Church, like Weeds in a new-digg'd Garden, had not our renouncing them kept them in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some poor, low, narrow ſpirited Men, ſuperſtitious and miſled, are for this Way, as the only way of Entrance and Continuance in the Churches Service; Spirits ſo poor that they cannot afford one token of Charity to Diſſenters, as if ſuch a Spiritual Alms, would undo them; ſo low, that having never ſtood upon the Shoulders of Wiſdom and Experience, they ſee not the Latitude of the way of Heaven; ſo narrow-hearted, that he thinks there is no room for any in Church-Communion, eſpecially in the Miniſtry, that will not go into, and ſtand in a little Frame, like that in which he ſtands, like an Image. His Charity may extend to the Salvation of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, (a Notion pretty rife) but not to the Toleration of Chriſtians, eſpecially of Preachers of the common Salvation, if they will not conform. Papiſts ſhall ſooner enter into the Kingdom of God, than a Presbyterian. And who is the Presbyterian? He may be a Biſhop, a Lord a Parliament-Man, yea a whole Parliament, a Lord Mayor, if but moderate, as well as a preaching moderate <hi>Conformiſt.</hi> The Moderate of all Qualities, is the Presbyterian; but the Presbyterians are not moderate: No, a Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, is an out-witted Jeſuit, and a Jeſuit is an overwitting Presbyterian. Theſe new Character-makers are at this Wit: and ſeeing he would be a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50217:33"/>Wit that makes the Character, I doubt not, but he is for <hi>being</hi> of the greateſt ſort of Wits, that is, the over-witting Presbyterian. This piece of Formality makes himſelf and the Government all one, that muſt be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, thinks he, if any thing be abaſed that varies from his Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Model, and Meaſure of his Aſſent. He is not a Papiſt, ſomething keeps him off; but, good Man, he hath high thoughts of the old Way; every Ceremony is in his Eye, a kind of a hallowed thing; and the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Church, is wrapped in the Rag of Antiquity, which never was a piece of a Garment in faſhion in the Apoſtles days, or ſome Centuries af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: He contends for the gray Hairs which grow over the Eyes of the Church, and the Nails which have pinched and nipt many tender Skins, as for the Life and Soul of Religion. Many are miſled by their Informers, not in Antiquity only, but in Modern Times, even in their own Days, or the days of their immediate Fathers. The Times of War and Uſurpation, are the only ill Times in their Chronicles; which were ill indeed, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Puniſhment and Sin; but have nothing but good to ſay of the ill Times of Provocation, of Peace proceeding. They do moſt partially and untruly charge the War upon the Presbyterians. Much more falſly upon Praying and Preaching; or the Divines that were in the <hi>Parliament</hi> Quarters, and City, many of which were forced thither. It was as truly a <hi>Popiſh Plot</hi> and <hi>War,</hi> and, at firſt, between Prerogative and Liberty, tho not ſo bare-faced as this horrid Plot. Theſe Men are abuſed by ſome of our Deceiving Writers, and know as little of what they declaim againſt, as they do of the Diſſenters of this preſent Age. But <hi>Addabatorum more pugnant; &amp; clamores (quantos!) excitant.</hi>—It was a bloody Civil War, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly about Civil Matters; it was called <hi>Bellum Epiſopale,</hi> not by ſome Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament-Men only, but one Biſhop, or more; to make the riſing Clergy part with their Mony to maintain it; but it was <hi>Bellum Papale pro Rege, contra Regem,</hi> as well as againſt Parliament and Proteſtants.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Our perſecuting Fire-brands, are againſt Proteſtant Peace and Union. They approve of perſecuting Laws, if they might have a Parliament to make them; and it ſhall not be perſecution againſt Diſſenting Proteſtants, but Juſtice, becauſe it is but the Execution of Laws: and Diſſenters muſt be undone, to preſerve the Law and Government. How freely do they exclaim againſt it, cloſly gird at our laſt Parliament? fly upon our Bleſſed Reformation from Popery; blemiſh it with Aſperſions of Sedition and Rebellion (an Affront to Religion not to be endured.) [If they read no more than Dr. <hi>Du Moulin,</hi> Pr. of <hi>Canterbury</hi>'s Anſwer to <hi>Philanax Anglieus,</hi> they will be more juſt to the Reformation.] Theſe Men are ſo well prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for a Popiſh Succeſſor, that they can truſt God with their Religion, tho in Popiſh Hands, (And cannot they truſt themſelves too?) but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:50217:33"/>truſt a Non-conforming Proteſtant, with preaching a Sermon, or Praying, not in an open Pulpit. Theſe blow up Controverſies into unquenchable diſſentions, into large Differences, into wide Chaſms, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſable Gulfs. They condemn the Magiſtrate for Coldneſs, if he let a Diſſenter preach, or leave him a Bed to lie upon. The Ejected are like Suburbs, without the Walls of Uniformity, burn the Suburbs to ſave the Church within; whereas one would think it were the ſafer way, to build a Wall about the Suburbs, and bring them within the Line. They hate Houſe-preaching, and running into Corners, and would bring out the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> into the Sun-ſhine, but only in the <hi>Dog-days. Caniculum Perſecutio tui video.</hi> Tertull. <hi>Parce Civibus Miles,</hi> is Heathen Latin; but <hi>Occide &amp; manduca,</hi> is in the Original.</p>
               <p>It was a ſevere word of King <hi>James; If this be all</hi> (quoth he) <hi>which they have to ſay,</hi> (meaning our famous Dr. <hi>Jo. Rainolds,</hi> and the other Divines, called <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi>) <hi>I ſhall make them Conform themſelves, or I will hurry them out of this Land, or elſe do worſe.</hi> [<hi>Conference at</hi> Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-Court. <hi>p.</hi> 85.] It is as likely that they know not what Spirit they are of, that are for hurrying good Men, as it was from a Spirit of Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, that a Lord ſaid, He was perſuaded the King ſpoke in that Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence by the Holy Ghoſt. How well ſoever he ſpake in ſome parts of it, yet that ſaying might have been ſpared.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Idle and inſufficient Miniſters, that live at eaſe, and as the manner of ſpeaking is, enjoy themſelves, that are more Abroad than at Home, and as ſeldom in their Studies, as they are in their Pulpits, are indiſpoſed to a Cloſure. Theſe Conform perhaps above Conformity ſometimes, whoſe Surplices are as Cloaks for their Faults; and their pretended Loyalty makes them impregnable againſt deſerved Cenſures. Many of theſe conſort with Companions of a Feather, inflame one another into a degree of madneſs. Theſe drive away their People, and when they are gone, throw after them, and revile thoſe that entertain them better. Theſe, with all their Might, cry, the Church, the Church; declaim againſt much preaching, (and is not that a good way to ſave their pains, by calling it needleſs?) We are not now to convert Heathens, (they would rather confirm than convert them) much preaching hath ſpoiled the World; I hate theſe Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, nothing will ſerve them but Preaching; cry out againſt <hi>Calvin,</hi> the Parliament, the Fanaticks, and run over their Railery, as Papiſts do their Beads. Theſe are afraid of admiſſion of more good Preachers, that their Manners will be inſpected, and their Churches quite deſerted; that they muſt take more and better pains, or elſe be expoſed.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Eccleſiaſtical Merchants, <hi>Eccleſiae Poſſeſſivae Filii,</hi> are againſt admiſſion of more to the exerciſe of the Sacred Function. The Trade hath been in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50217:34"/>ſome great Mens Hands, and the engroſſing of the Commodities of the Church, hath enriched many, that never would have touched the Burden with one of their Fingers, but for double Wages. But if more Miniſters are capacitated by Law, the Endowments of the Church will be diſtributed into more hands. Theſe turn Prophets, that the Church will fall, when due Encouragements are taken away from Learned Men, in which Rank they place themſelves; <hi>q. d.</hi> Take away Pluralities, you diſcourage Learning; whereas it is too well known to both our Univerſities, that they are a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to Learning, that many are not rewarded with a Plurality, for their double Portion of Learning; and that the Learning of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, is as much the Ornament and Support of the Church as theirs, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of whoſe Abſence is as profitable to their Pariſhes, (except to the Poor, who have no Alms at their Doors, nor relief from the Parſonage) as their Preſence. Theſe are potent in their Patrons, Friends, and Relations, and may obſtruct the Work, when things come to the Vote, and Fleſh and Blood pleads Reaſon againſt the true Intereſt of Religion, and the crying Neceſſity of Souls. But let them not fear, for there is no danger of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them out, to bring others in; Nor do the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> deſire their Liberty with the deprivation of any now in poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Some honeſt and good Men are afraid of an Alteration from a miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Caſe. Many ran into Conformity to be out of Confuſion, and are now tenacious of this Conformity, for fear of a Toleration of Popery, and Antichriſtian Sects. But there are Mediums between Extreams.<note place="margin">The Non-conformiſts offered to Conform to Arch-Biſhop <hi>Uſher</hi>'s Model.—</note> They argue in their haſte, from the Neceſſity of a Church-Government, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an abatement of Rigor, as if the ſodering of Parties, would be a throwing of all into the Fire, and the running of the whole into a ſhapeleſs and formleſs Lump. Many are boldly impoſed upon into an ill Opinion of our Parliament, and compoſing Minds, as if they deſigned a Diſſolution of Government; and indeed do, by their cauſleſs Fears, diſcover the ill temper of our Cement, that if you do but touch our preſent Church Frame, it will be in danger of falling.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Some are warped from a Cloſure, by the influence of Self-love: They have Conformed, and are afraid of an after-condemnation for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, and that the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> will come in as Victors, and be puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed up into an oſtentation of their Refuſal and Sufferings upon better Grounds and Principles. But Brotherly-love and Self-denial, which are ſo eſſential to Chriſtianity, muſt be our Exerciſe, carrying on the common Salvation with one Heart and Shoulder.—But theſe two laſt named, will not be grieved at our Union, when it appears to be good.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:50217:34"/>
Laſtly; Our many Breaches with God, is the great Gulf between. On the one hand, if Church-men would lay to Heart, and mourn for our Diviſions, and clearly ſee whence they ariſe, and the great Loſs to the Church at home, and Scandal to the Churches abroad, by the Ejection of ſo many able good Men, whom no other Nation could ſpare, and turn the Heat of Diſputation into Love and Compaſſion, and ſpare themſelves by not diſgracing others, we might have more hopes. That Doctor (I conceal his Name, for he is fallen aſleep) who ſaw <hi>London</hi>-fire, and was deeply affected with it, who after his return to his Place in the Country on the Faſt following, reckoned this among the many Sins, and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Provocations of the Land, that many able Miniſters were tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of the Miniſtry, was in a right temper for a Solemn Faſt, but was chidden and rated into Tears for his melting Charity, by his angry Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan. On the other Hand, when diſſenting Chriſtians, or Auditors, bring forth more Fruit under the unwearied Labours of their Preachers, and obey the Goſpel of Chriſt, and can bleſs God for the many able pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Preachers, and receive the Faith and Word, without reſpect of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and be ſorry for their Anger and evil-ſpeaking, we may come to an Union, and ſee the Partition-Wall thrown down.</p>
               <p>But ſurely our Legiſlators are too wiſe, and more reſolved upon the moſt neceſſary Work of compoſing Differences, than to endanger the whole by a diviſion of Parts; to gratify theſe, I have named who are not of ſo much worth, as to compenſate the loſs of publick Church-Proteſtant-Peace for their ſakes.—</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Caſe and Qualifications of the <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> is ſuch, as no good Man of any Spirit ſhould be afraid to own, by way of Interceſſion, or Solicitation for their readmiſſion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thoſe few that are yet alive, who were Men before the War, are as ſafe under the Healing Wings of the Act of Grace, as any other Men who needed that Protection as much as they, and have been placed as near the King and Court, as they have been driven from him. The greater is their Tranſgreſſion, who peck at that Foundation of our Peace, and that tear that Covering from their Neighbours backs, in their Pulpits and Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They need no more Clemency, nor Pardons, ſince, than other Men, except for their Preaching.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They are admitted into the private Converſe of the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent of all Qualities in the Land, except a few. Who can ſay of any of them, with ſuch an one, no not to Eat? Therefore they are admittable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a publick Station, where they can do more good, and leſs hurt, if do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hurt were their Deſign and Faculty, than in private. Me-thinks no
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50217:35"/>Man ſhould be permitted to preach to five, and from five to five, from Houſe to Houſe, that may not be permitted to preach publickly: For may they with Safety, and Edification to Souls, preach to five at a time, why not to five hundred at a time? Or if their preaching in publick be dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the State and Church, is it not much more in private? Our Prieſts and Jeſuits have not perverted their boaſted of Numbers in publick, but in private. Families are the Nurſeries of Church and State; corrupt them, and the poiſon is diſperſed. Me-thinks it ſhould not be at all law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> to preach to a number not exceeding five at once, or as lawful to preach in publick; where if they were a Depraving, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Sect of Men, (which they are not) but to be preferred before thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands that Officiate in the Land, they will be more wary and temperate, than to loſe their Hearers, or hazard their Liberty, which they obtain with ſo much difficulty. Suppoſe twenty Non-conforming Miniſters ſhould keep ſtrictly to their legal number of five; theſe twenty Miniſters preach to a hundred Citizens; if theſe twenty ſhould Lecture the hundred into Atheiſm, Blaſphemy, Infidelity, Hereſy, Sedition or Rebellion, would it be endured? would not the Peſtilence ſpread? And that of the Mind is as quickly diffuſed, and as ſilently conveyed, as the <hi>Plague</hi> from Body to Body, and Houſe to Houſe. If they are Men of pernicious Principles, they are allowed too much; if not, they are allowed too little. It is true, they have taken Liberty contrary to Law, to preach to greater Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and have patiently born the Penalties, when inflicted. And by their adventuring, they have vindicated themſelves, and teſtified to the Goſpel which they believe, and ſtop'd the Mouths of many; beſides much good done upon many thouſand Souls, that had been elſe neglected; and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the World what manner of Men they are, what Doctrine they preach, and that they have not ſowed Sedition, and ill Principles of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty and Treaſons: And the many Years experience, and proof given of their Principles and Abilities, is not only an Apology for them, againſt them that judg them, <hi>vel prejudicio nominis,</hi> but furniſh the Wiſe and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate with ſome Arguments to plead for reaſonable Abatements for them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They have done as much as any Men of their Degrees, to ſupport and ſave the Nation, and the Proteſtant Profeſſion, and as great a Terror to the Papiſts, as any of their number and quality in the Land: And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, if they thought that either Popery, or any Antichriſtian Sects ſhould enter in by them, though they cannot conform to keep them out, by that, they would ask leave to remove into other Nations, rather than be a Door to let in Miſeries upon their own.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:50217:35"/>
5. They are Men of great Parts, Piety, and Prudence, ſound Divines, good Preachers and Writers; no Man that knows their Perſons, or their Labours, or their Writings, but ought to give them their due, without detraction from others. With what a ſweet Spirit and Stile, Learning, Judgment, Argument, hath Mr. <hi>Polehill</hi> vindicated them, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Church, againſt Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Imputations?</p>
               <p n="6">6. Wiſe and great Men for Power, Place, Wiſdom, and Experience in Affairs, both of Church and State, have endeavoured a Compoſition, though in vain: I ſhould not be aſhamed or afraid, to my beſt ability, to commend the Endeavours of but one Lord Keeper <hi>Bridgman;</hi> of but one Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hales</hi> (What would we have given for him ſince his Death?) of but one Biſhop <hi>Wilkins,</hi> or either of the Deans of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>Pauls.</hi> But I have ſhewed how ſome of the ſharpeſt Procurers of our Laws grew mild and gentle. But beſide thoſe venerable Perſons, the Right Reverend Biſhops, <hi>Reynolds, Gawden,</hi> were tenderly affected, as was Biſhop <hi>Earle;</hi> and as the now moſt learned Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> as I have it from a good hand, the Biſhop of <hi>Hereford,</hi> beſide others, more than I can or will name, of eminent worth in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And ſurely, rigor, and ſuppreſſion of ſo ſound a number of Miniſters, doth neither become Men, as Wiſe, Experienced, Self-ſearchers, Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; or to deſcend below a Chriſtian, it is not humane nor genteel. The more wiſe, experienced, ſelf-acquainted, Chriſtian, or genteel any Man is, the more moderate in Ceremonies, different Rites, and Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. [See the cloſe of theſe Sheets.]</p>
               <p n="7">7. I never heard any Wiſe, Learned, good Man of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> juſtify their Ejection, nor approve of their Suppreſſion; ſome have wiſhed they would give way to the Wrath of angry Magiſtrates, either by abſtaining from publick Preaching, or in time of Publick, that they might eſcape the edg of the Law.</p>
               <p n="8">8. It is no more to their prejudice that they are not all of the ſame mind, than that we are not all of a mind, no not in the point of Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="9">9. To intercede for them, and their admiſſion, is not to plead for tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent, factious, ſchiſmatical Perſons, that are inſufferable. Make them one with us by a Law, and where is the Faction, and Schiſm? Suppoſe the King and Parliament for them, and againſt us; their way made legal, and ours as it is, only by a voluntary Profeſſion, as tied up to it in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but without or againſt the Law; on whom would the charge of Schiſm fall? The Magiſtrates Favour and Law removes, or faſtens the Crime. I know there is a Schiſm, and it is a great Sin, without reſpect to humane Laws; but he that endeavours to keep the Unity of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:50217:36"/>the Spirit, in the Bond of Peace, is no Schiſmatick, although he cannot come up to the Terms of Conformity. I have a tenderneſs in imputing Schiſm to any good Men, who cannot live and die in Sin; but if this be a ſin, many good Men have died in it, never declaring their Repentance for their Non-conformity, or Preaching againſt the Prohibition of the Law. I do verily believe they were not only ſeemingly, but ſincerely good Men; 'tis too hard to judg them dead in Sin.</p>
               <p n="10">10. They are Proteſtants; if they come not to that Teſt, reject them; they are peaceable, they are loyal, are true to the King according to Law, they have born their burden with us. Do we pray for the King, ſo do they, and for all that are in Authority, that under them they may lead peaceable and quiet lives in all godlineſs and honeſty? Do we Faſt? they do the ſame, with great importunity. Who more abundant in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours than they? Who more Orthodox according to the Doctrines of the Church than they?—My Paper is almoſt at an end, and ſo am I.</p>
               <p>Thus I have communicated my Thoughts with great plainneſs and truth. I ſhall ſay what was once ſpoken in Parliament. <q>Let us firſt fear God, then ſhall we honour the King the more, for I am afraid we have been leſs proſperous in Parliaments, becauſe we have preferred other Matters before him. Let Religion be our <hi>Primum Quaerite,</hi> for all things elſe are but <hi>Et caetera's</hi> to it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> [Sir <hi>Ben. Rudyer.</hi>]</p>
               <p>And whether Excluſion of Papiſts, or Incluſion of Proteſtants be firſt endeavoured, is left to the Wiſdom of my Superiors.—God proſper both.</p>
               <p>For my Brethren and Companion's ſake, I will now pray; <hi>Peace be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Violentis Conſiliis, nec ſanari mentes, nec tranquillitas Eccleſiae reſtitui unquam poterit.</hi> [Phil. Melanch. <hi>ad</hi> Hen. 2. Fran. Reg.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod ſi ſquamnae Leviathan ità cohoereant, ut earum opere textili denſato, quaſi Loricatus incedat Satan &amp; Cataphractus, quod de</hi> ſoedere Concordiae, <hi>quâ malignantis Eccleſiae Membra, ſe complexa, muniunt &amp; circumvallent. Elegantiſſimè</hi> Lutherus <hi>&amp; verè, cur immane quantum hient, obſecro, quaſi ruinam <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſae Fabricae minitantes, inhient<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quaſi vaſto foedo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> rictu ſe devoraturi, vivi Lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in vero Templo Collocati,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>inquit Dr.</hi> Stoughton. <hi>Epiſtola Elegantiſſ. cui Titulus, Foelicitas ultimi Soeculi.</hi> p. 40.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="addenda">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:50217:36"/>
            <head>Addenda.</head>
            <p>I Will fill up theſe Sheets with ſome Royal Condeſcenſions, and Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Pleas, (beſides thoſe mentioned before) which I humbly entreat thoſe in Authority, eſpecially my Lords the Biſhops, ſeriou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly to conſider, in behalf of the <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> which may be found in his Majeſty's Speeches and Declaration about Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, and ſome of the Biſhops own writing. And firſt obſerve what his preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſays concering the <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In his Declaration of Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, <hi>Octob.</hi> 25. 1660. <q>When We were in <hi>Holland,</hi> (ſays he) We were attended by many Grave and Learned Miniſters from hence, who were looked upon as moſt able and principal Aſſertors of the Presbyterian Opinions, with whom We had as much Conference, as the multitude of Affairs, which were then upon Us, would permit Us to have; and to Our great ſatisfaction and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, found them Perſons full of Affection to Us, of Zeal for the Peace of the Church and State, and neither Enemies (as they have been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven out to be) to Epiſcopy, or Liturgy, but moſtly to deſire ſuch Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in either, as without ſhaking Foundations, might allay the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Diſtempers, which the Indiſpoſition of the Time, and tenderneſs of ſome Mens Conſciences had contracted. —</q>
            </p>
            <p>And concerning Ceremonies, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. he ſays, <q>Now We do not think that Reverence We have for the <hi>Church of England</hi> in the leaſt degree di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed by our Condeſcenſions, not peremptorily to inſiſt on ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of Ceremonies; which how-ever introduced by the Piety and Devotion, and order of former Times, may not be ſo agreeable to the preſent, but may even leſſen that Piety and Devotion; for the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof, they might happily be firſt introduced, and conſequently may well be <hi>diſpenſed with;</hi> and we hope this charitable Compliance of Ours, will diſpoſe the minds of all Men to a chearful ſubmiſſion to that Authority, the preſervation whereof is ſo neceſſary for the Unity and Peace of the Church; and that they will believe the ſupport of the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:50217:37"/>Epiſcopal Authority, to be the beſt ſupport of Religion, by being the means to contain the minds of Men within the Rules of Government.</q> And <hi>pag.</hi> 16.—<q>And therefore Our preſent Conſideration and Work is, to gratify the private Conſciences of thoſe who are grieved with the uſe of ſome Ceremonies, by indulging to, and diſpenſing with, their omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe Ceremonies.</q>—</p>
            <p>And <hi>pag.</hi> 7, 8.—<q>As for what concerns the Penalties upon thoſe who (living peaceably) do not conform thereunto, (<hi>viz.</hi> the Act of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity) through ſcruple and tenderneſs of Conſcience, but modeſtly without ſcandal perform their Devotions in their own way. We ſhall make it our ſpecial Care, ſo far forth as in us lies, without invading the freedom of Parliament to incline their Wiſdom,—to concur with Us in the making ſome ſuch Act for that purpoſe, as may enable Us to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe with a more univerſal Satisfaction.—That Power of Diſpencing which We conceive to be inherent in Us: Nor can We doubt of their chearful cooperating with us in a thing wherein we do conceive our ſelves ſo far engaged in Honour, and in what we owe to the Peace of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; which We profeſs We can never think ſecure, whilſt there ſhall be a colour left to the Malicious and Diſaffected, to inflame the minds of ſo many Multitudes upon the ſcore of Conſcience, with deſpair of ever obtaining any effect of our Promiſes for their Eaſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And in his Speech to both Houſes of Parliament, <hi>Feb.</hi> 10. 1667. ſaith He,—<q>One thing more I hold my Self obliged to recommend unto you at this preſent; which is, That you would ſeriouſly think of ſome courſe to beget a better Union and Compoſure in the minds of my Proteſtant Subjects, in Matters of Religion; whereby they may be induced, not only to ſubmit quietly to the Government, but alſo chearfully give their aſſiſtance to the ſupport of it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And in his Speech to both Houſes, <hi>Nov.</hi> 9. 1678. He ſaith, <q>I meet you here with the moſt earneſt deſire that Man can have, to unite the Minds of all my Subjects, both to <hi>Me,</hi> and to <hi>one another;</hi> and I reſolve it ſhall be your Fault, if the Succeſs be not ſutable to my Deſires.—Beſides, that end of Union which I aim at, (and which I wiſh could be extended to Proteſtants Abroad, as well as at Home): I purpoſe by this laſt ſtep I have made, to diſcern whether the Proteſtant Religion, and the Peace of the Kingdom, be as truly aimed at by others, as they are really intended by Me.</q>—</p>
            <p>Some Biſhops formerly, and of late, have moſt pathetically pleaded the Caſe of the <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> whoſe Apoſtolical Zeal and Charity are worthy the Conſideration and Imitation of the preſent Biſhops and Fathers of our Church at this Time eſpecially. A former Biſhop of St. <hi>Davids,</hi> in the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:50217:37"/>Convocation-Houſe, <hi>May</hi> 23. 1604. — ſpeaking of thoſe who were ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous only upon ſome Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <q>Being otherwiſe Learned, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, grave, and honeſt Men, whoſe Labours have been painful in the Church, and profitable to their ſeveral Congregations, (he ſays) tho I do not juſtify their Doings, yet ſurely their Service would be miſſed at ſuch a Time; as need ſhall require them and us to give the right hand of Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip one to another, and to go Arm in Arm againſt the common Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, that ſo there might be <hi>Vis unita fortior.</hi>—If theſe our Brethren a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid ſhould be deprived of their Places, for the Matters premiſed, I think we ſhould find cauſe to bend our Wits to the uttermoſt extent of our skill to provide ſome Cure of Souls for them, where they may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe their Talents.— Furthermore, if theſe Men, being divers hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, (as it is bruited abroad) ſhould forſake their Charges, (as ſome do preſuppoſe they will) who, I pray you, ſhould ſucceed them? — Beſides this, for ſo much as in the Life-time of the late Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> theſe things were not ſo extreamly urged, but that many Learned Preachers enjoyed their Liberty herein, conditionally that they did not by Word or Deed openly diſgrace or diſturb the State eſtabliſhed; I would know a Reaſon, why it ſhould not be ſo generally and exceeding ſtrictly called upon, eſpecially conſidering theſe Men are now the more neceſſary, by ſo much as we ſee greater encreaſe of Papiſts to be now of late, than were before. To conclude, I wiſh, that if by Petition made to the King's Majeſty, there cannot be obtained a quite remove of the Premiſes, which ſeem ſo grievous to divers, nor yet a Toleration for them which be of the more ſtaid and temperate carriage, yet at the leaſt, there might be procured a mitigation of the Penalty, if they cannot be drawn by other Reaſons to a Conformity with us.</q> Thus far this Biſhop in thoſe days, when the Terms of Conformity were not ſo hard.</p>
            <p>The preſent Lord Biſhop of <hi>Hereford,</hi> in his <hi>Naked Truth,</hi> with hearty Compaſſion and Zeal, pleads the Caſe of our preſent <hi>Non-conformiſts,</hi> both with the (then) two Houſes of Parliament, and the Biſhops in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.— Firſt, In his Addreſs to the Lords and Commons in general, he thus expreſſes himſelf; <q>My Lords and Noble Gentlemen, you have fully expreſſed your Zeal to God, and his Church, in making Laws for Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I call God, the ſearcher of all Hearts, the God of Life and Death, to witneſs, That I would moſt readily, yea, moſt joyfully ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice all I have in this World, my Life and all, that all <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> were reduced to our Church; but it falls out moſt ſadly, that your Laws have not the deſired effect, our Church is more and more divided, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>— And concludes, with earneſt Prayers, <q>That God would direct them to that which may make for the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> by yeelding to weak Ones, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>—</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:50217:38"/>
And in <hi>pag.</hi> 10. (Edition in <hi>Folio</hi>) he thus earneſtly and ſeriouſly Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes him to the Biſhops; <q>My Reverend Fathers and Judges of the Church, I (with St. <hi>Paul, Col.</hi> 3.) beſeech you put on fatherly <hi>bowels of Mercies, Kindneſs, humbleneſs of Mind, Meekneſs, Long-ſuffering</hi> towards your poor weak Children; and ſo long as they hold faſt the Body of Chriſt, be not ſo rigorous with them for Shadows; if they ſubmit to you in Subſtance, have patience, tho they do not ſubmit in Ceremonies: and give me leave to tell you my poor Opinion; This violent preſſing of Ceremonies hath (I humbly conceive) been a great hinderance from em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing them, Men fearing your Intentions to be far worſe than really they are, and therefore abhor them.</q>—</p>
            <p>And <hi>pag.</hi> 11.— <q>This force-urging Uniformity in Worſhip, hath cauſed great diviſion in Faith, as well as Charity; for had you, by aboliſhing ſome Ceremonies, taken the weak Brethren into your Church, they had not wandred about after ſeducing Teachers, nor fallen into ſo many groſs Opinions of their own.— Now I beſeech you, in the fear of God, ſet before your Eyes the dreadful Day of Judgment, when Chriſt in his Tribunal of Juſtice ſhall require an account of every Word and Deed, and ſhall thus queſtion you: Here are ſeveral Souls, who taking offence at <hi>your</hi> Ceremonies, have forſaken my Church, have forſaken the Faith, have run into Hell, the Souls for which I ſhed my precious Blood; Why have you ſuffered this? Nay, why have you occaſioned this? Will you Anſwer, It was to preſerve <hi>our</hi> Ceremonies? Will not Chriſt return unto you, Are <hi>your</hi> Ceremonies more dear unto you than the Souls for which I died? Who hath required theſe things at your hands? Will you, for Ceremonies, which you your ſelves confeſs to be indifferent, no way neceſſary unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, ſuffer your weak Brethren to periſh, for whom I died? Have not I ſhewed you how <hi>David and his Souldiers were guiltleſs in eating the Shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread, which was not lawful but only for the Prieſts to eat?</hi> If <hi>David</hi> diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a Ceremony commanded by God, to ſatisfy the hunger of his People, Will not you diſpence with <hi>your own</hi> Ceremonies to ſatisfy the Souls of my People, who are called by my Name, and profeſs my Name, tho in weakneſs? Or will you tell Chriſt, they ought to ſuffer for their own wilfulneſs and perverſeneſs, who will not ſubmit to the Laws of the Church as they ought? Will not Chriſt return, Shall they periſh for tranſgreſſing <hi>your</hi> humane Laws, which they ignorantly conclude Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, And ſhall not you periſh for tranſgreſſing my Divine Laws, which you know to be Good and Holy? Had I mercy on you, and ſhould not you have mercy on you fellow Servants? With the ſame meaſure you meeted, it ſhall be meaſured unto you again: I tremble to go farther, but moſt humbly beſeech you, for Chriſt's ſake, endeavour to regain theſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:50217:38"/>ſtrayed Sheep, for which he ſhed his precious Blood, and think it as great an advantage, as great an honour to you, as it was to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to become all things to all Men, that you may gain ſome, as doubtleſs you will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, tho not all; and the few ſtanders off will be the more convinced, and at long running wearied out and gained alſo.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I cloſe this Biſhop's earneſt Requeſts, with one of the Prayers made by the Biſhops, for the late Faſt on <hi>Decemb.</hi> 22. 1680. appointed by the King's Proclamation, (among other ends) to Unite the Hearts of all Loyal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, (and I hope my Lords the Biſhops will join their ſincere endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours with this devout Prayer.) <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For Union among our Selves.</head>
               <p>BLeſſed Jeſu, our Saviour, and our Peace; who didſt ſhed thy precious Blood upon the Croſs, that thou might ſt aboliſh, and deſtroy all Enmity among Men, and reconcile them in one Body unto God: Look down in much pity and compaſſion upon this diſtreſſed Church, and Nation; who's bleeding Wounds, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd by the lamentable Diviſions that are among us, cry aloud for thy ſpeedy Help, and ſaving Relief. Stir up, we beſeech thee, every Soul of us, carefully (as becomes ſincere Chriſtians) to root out of our Hearts all Pride, and Vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, all Wrath and Bitterneſs, all unjuſt Prejudice and cauſleſs Jealouſy, all Hatred and Malice, and deſire of Revenge, and whatſoever it is, that may any way exaſperate our Minds, or hinder us from diſcerning the things that belong unto our Peace: And by the Power of thy Holy Spirit of Peace, diſpoſe all our Hearts to ſuch meekneſs of Wiſdom, and lowlineſs of Mind, ſuch calm and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate Long-ſuffering, and Forbearance of one another in Love, with ſuch due eſteem of thoſe, whom thou haſt ſet over us to watch for our Souls, as may turn the Hearts of the Fathers to the Children, and the Hearts of the Children to the Fathers; that ſo we may become a ready People prepar'd to live in Peace, and the God of Peace may be with us. To this End, give us all Grace, O Lord, ſeriouſly to lay to heart, not only the great Dangers we are in at preſent by theſe unhappy Diviſions, but alſo the great Obligations to this godly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, and Concord, which lie upon us: That as there is but one Body, and one Spirit, and one Hope of our Calling; one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one God, and Father of all; ſo we may henceforth be all of one Heart, and of one Soul, cloſely united in one holy bond of Truth and Peace, of Faith and Charity; and may with one Mind and one Mouth glorify thee, O Lord, the Prince of Peace, who with thy bleſſed Father, in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Holy Spirit, liveſt, and reigneſt ever one God World without end.<hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
